<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Runne from Rome. Or, A treatise shevving the necessitie of separating from the Church of Rome Disputed in these termes: euerie man is bound vpon paine of damnation to refuse the faith of the Church of Rome. By Antony Wotton. B.D.</title>
            <author>Wotton, Anthony, 1561?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120314</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855513</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1125:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Runne from Rome. Or, A treatise shevving the necessitie of separating from the Church of Rome Disputed in these termes: euerie man is bound vpon paine of damnation to refuse the faith of the Church of Rome. By Antony Wotton. B.D.</title>
                  <author>Wotton, Anthony, 1561?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W[illiam] I[ones] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the south side of the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Necessity of separation from the Church of Rome.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint 1542-1621 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:1"/>
            <p>RVNNE FROM ROME. <hi>OR</hi> A TREATISE SHEWING THE neceſſitie of Separating from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſputed in theſe Termes:</hi> EVERIE MAN IS bound vpon paine of Damnation to refuſe the Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ANTONY WOTTON. B. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. 18. 4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not Partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. J.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the South ſide of the Royall-Exchange. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE <hi>EDWARD</hi> LORD DENNY OF WALTHAM, MY ESPECIALL GOOD LORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the great God of heauen and earth proclaimed by his Prophet to</hi> Eli, 1. <hi>Sam. 2. 30 that</hi> he would honor them that honour him; <hi>he therein implied, both an example and a charge for all men to do the like. Therefore is this actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of honouring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that honour God, one of thoſe whereof the holy Ghoſt made choiſe, Pſal. 15. 4. that he might by them giue vs notice of thoſe men which</hi> ſhal abide in the Tabernacle of the Lord, and dwell in his holy hill. <hi>It is my deſire to performe this dutie to God, by this ſeruice to your Lordſhip: wherein I feele and confeſſe, that I receiue far more then I can poſsibly giue. For by deſiring to honour our Lordſhip for your zeale in honouring God, I</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21008:3"/> encreaſe mine owne hope, that I am of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who haue obtained already ſome part of his grace, and ſhall hereafter haue entrance into his glorie. Giue me leaue (noble Lord) to forget, in this reſpect, my particular obligation to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for your continuall bountie to me, and good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of me, that I haue an vnfained deſire to maintaine the truth of God, profeſt in this famous Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt the ſubtill and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous errors of the Romiſh Synagogue. For I truly and willingly profeſſe, that the conſideration of your Lordſhips feruent zeale for the glory of God, zealous loue of his truth, and true deteſtation of Popery, haue ſo poſſeſt and rauiſht my heart with a longing after your Honour, that it will not ſuffer any other of your noble vertues (though many and great) either to come into compariſon with it, or to haue the leaſt place in my thoughts, while it is in preſence. This (in my apprehenſion) is as much to true honour, as in <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> opinion, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation was to true eloquence. Let them, that will dote, vpon their worldly greatneſſe, as the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke is in loue with his owne feathers. It is true honour to be honourable in his ſight, who onely is worthy of honour; and yet graciouſly vouchſafeth to giue and to command that honour be giue to
<pb facs="tcp:21008:3"/> his faithfull ſeruants. This is the foundation of your Lordſhips honour in my heart, and vpon this ground wil I daily offer vp my poore prayers to God for your good Lordſhip, your noble and truly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, and hopefull of ſpring, that it would pleaſe him to ſhewer downe euery day more &amp; more the comfortable dew of his grace and bleſsing vpon euery one of you, to the increaſe of all honour in this life, and happineſſe in the life to come, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In whom I ſhall euer be at your Lordſhips ſeruice to be commanded, Antony Wotton.</signed>
               <dateline>Tower-Hill <date>May 3. 1624.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Councell of Trent confirmed by the Pope, is the chiefe Oracle of the Church of Rome: from it ſhe receiues all doctrines neceſſarie to be beleeued vnto ſaluation; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholikes hold it for a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that whatſoeuer is deliuered therein for doctrine, is an article of faith, and muſt ſtedfaſtly be beleeued vpon paine of damnation: he that doth not, is pronounced an Hereticke, and is made lyable to a (ſuppoſed) heauy curſe. What little reaſon there is that Papiſts ſhould yeeld ſuch blind obedience to the Canons of that Councell, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by a plaine (but true) teſtimonie which was giuen thereunto by a Biſhop, a member of that Church and Councell, who was preſent thereat; This teſtimonie I haue thought good to prefixe to this my Treatiſe, becauſe in it I diſpute againſt the doctrine of faith deliuered in the ſaid Councell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Andraeas Dudithius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Quinqueccleſiae,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quinqueccleſiae, is acitty in Lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in German <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rchin in Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nden or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and Embaſſadour in the Councell of Trent for Maximilan the ſecond Emperour: in an Epiſtle to the ſaid Emperour, (wherein he deliuereth his iudgement about granting the Cup to the
<pb facs="tcp:21008:4"/> Laitie, and the marriage of Prieſts,) writes thus of the Councell of Trent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHat good could be done in that Councell where voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were taken by number, not by weight? If argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if reaſon might haue preuailed, if we had had ſome and thoſe not many to take part with vs, though we ſhould haue bin but a few: yet had vve ouerthrowne the gre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>at forces of our aduerſaries: but when all ſtood vpon number, wherein we were much inferiour, we could not get the better, though our cauſe were the better. The Pope was able to ſet an hundreth of his againſt euery one of ours: and if an hundreth were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he could vpon a ſundaine haue created a thouſand to ſuccour them that were readie to faint and periſh. Therefore we might ſee euery day hungrie and needie Biſhops, and theſe for the moſt part beardleſſe younkers, and wastfully ryotous, come in flocks to Trent, hired to giue their voices according to the Popes humour, vnlearned indeed and fooliſh, but of good vſe to him for their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciouſneſſe and impudencie. When theſe fellowes were ioyued to the Popes old ſlatterers, then iniquitie got the vpper hand and triumphed: neither could any thing be decreed but according to their liking, who thought it the higheſt point of religion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the power and royot of the Pope. There was in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell a graue and learned man who could not endure this indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but the Councell by terrour threatning and bayting him as one that was no good Catholike, drew him to yeeld to that which he did no way like of. In a word, things are brought to that paſſe by their diſhoneſty who came prepared and made for the nonce, that it ſeemed to be a Councell not of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but of puppies: not of men, but of images, who (as it is reported of</hi> Daedalus <hi>Statues) were moued not by their owne but by other mens nerues, and muſcles. Thoſe hireling Biſhops moſt of them were like Countrey Bagpipes, which muſt haue breath blowne into them before they can ſound. The holy Ghoſt had nothing to doe with that Couenticle, all things were argued by human pollicy, which was wholly employed in maintaining the immoderate, &amp; indeed moſt ſhameleſſe Lordſhip &amp; Domination
<pb facs="tcp:21008:5"/> 
                  <hi>of the Popet. From thence were anſwers looked and wayted for, as it were from the Oracles of</hi> Delphos <hi>or</hi> Dodona: <hi>from thence the holy Ghoſt, who (as they brag) is Preſident of their Councell, was ſent ſhut vp in the Carriers budgets and packes, who (a thing worthy to be laught at) when the waters were vp as it falls out many times, was faine to ſtay till they were downe againe before he could repaire to the Councell. By this it came to paſſe that the Spirit was not carried vpon the waters as in</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis, but along beſides the waters. O monſtrous and incredible madnes! Nothing that the Biſhops as it were the Bodie of the Church reſolued of, could be of any force, vnleſſe it came firſt from the Pope as the head of the bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Epigramma</hi> G. B. <hi>de Rome et papa.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>Non ego Romulea miror quod Paſtor in vrbe</l>
               <l>Sceptra gerat, Paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conditor vrbis erat,</l>
               <l>Quumque lupae gentis nutritus lacte ſit Autor,</l>
               <l>Non ego Romulea miror in vrbo lupos.</l>
               <l>Haectantum ſuperat noſtrum admiratio captum,</l>
               <l>Quomodo ſecurum praeſtet ovile lupus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>The ſame tranſlated.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>It is not ſtrange a Shepheard raignes in Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For he that built it, was a Shepheards Groome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor is it ſtrange that wolues in Rome abound.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He ſuckt a wolſe, that did the Cittie found.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But this is ſtrange, and farre aboue my skill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How wolues ſhould keepe the flocke ſecure from ill.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declaring by way of Preface to the Reader, the matter and manner of this Treatiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good and carefull Phiſition, doth not onely prepare his portion according to Art, but alſo, if neede be, perſwade and intreate his patient to take it. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample I haue propounded to my ſelfe in this Treatiſe. In the former part whereof, I haue faithfully, and with the beſt skill I could vſe, prouided ſuch a medicine, as in it ſelfe is not vnfit, and (I hope) by the mercifull bleſſing of God, ſhall be made effectuall, to bring that to paſſe which is intended. My charge in this miniſtring is, rather a care to preuent what may happen, then a cure to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what hath happened. For the Papiſts, who are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die fallen into ſickneſſe, not onely like melancholicke men, refuſe all meanes of cure, vpon conceite that they neede it not; but alſo like <hi>Vliſſes</hi> companions, haue their eares ſtopped with the waxe of preiudice, and their eyes ſealed with blind obedience, that they can neither heare nor ſee in what caſe they are. I muſt therefore be content to let the mole thinke, that no creature can ſee better then ſhe, and apply my waters and powders to their eyes, who are rather weake ſighted, then ſtarke blind.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To you then I addreſſe my ſpeech (beloued Chriſtians) who ſee the truth, as he that had newly recouered his ſight, did iudge of men: he was able to perceiue they were men, but they ſeemed to him to be as high as trees: ſo that he ſaw what they were, but could not diſcerne their true proportion. So fareth it with a great part of thoſe, who profeſſe the Religion of God maintained in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21008:6"/> the Church of England: they haue a ſtrong perſwaſion that poperie is to be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſted, but they ſee not cleerely what it is tht maketh it deteſtable. <hi>Ioſuah</hi> and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael perceiued that the Lord was offended with <note place="margin">Ibſua 7. 7.</note> them, but could not find out <hi>Achan</hi> that had prouoked his diſpleaſuie. Behold, by Gods gracious aſſiſtance I haue found him out, attached, indited, and brought him to the barre, that all men may ſee the Babiloniſh ſtuffe which he hath conueyed into the campe of the liuing God, and hidden there in ſuch ſort, that he hath not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a long time beene taken for a true Iſraelite. Oh that it would pleaſe the Lord God, who onely can worke wonders, to giue him an heart and tongue to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie the Lord Ieſus by confeſſing of his theft, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him his honour: whereof vnder a colour of doing him ſeruice, he hath trai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erouſly robbed him.</p>
            <p>The proofe of this treaſon I leaue to the inſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and diſcourſe, with hope that I ſhall thereby (through Gods bleſſing) both inlighten the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and inſlame the affection with deteſtation of popiſh errours. It remaines, that (as briefly as I can,) I giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the courſe I haue taken in debating ſo weightie a matter. I haue herein gone a little out of the common high-way, into the by path of Schoole-learning: into which I either ſlipped, or thruſt my ſelfe, partly of choiſe, and partly of neceſſitie; Of choiſe, becauſe this kinde of writing in matters of this nature doth beſt content me; Of neceſſitie, becauſe I was aſraide, leaſt in ſo wide a ſea I might looſe my ſelfe, and either ouer ſhoote my port, or fall ſhort of it.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould I delight in ſuch thornie and vnbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wayes: dayly experience ſhewes how hard a thing it is to giue a reaſon of liking, and miſliking. All I will ſay is this. It is in ſtudies as in apparrell. There are that think large diſcourſes like looſe garments, and regard neither the fineneſſe of the ſtuffe, nor the neatneſſe of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-ſhip, but onely the fitneſſe for the bodie it muſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21008:6"/> ſerue. Theſe conſider what aptneſſe and force there is in that which is deliuered, to manifeſt and proue that which is vndertaken. Otherſome cannot abide to be kept to the point in queſtion, no more then to be pinioned in a ſtreight doublet; theſe men ſeeme to loue daintineſſe and eaſineſſe more then warmth and laſting: ſo that which they reade or write, pleaſe for the preſent, they care not greatly whether it be little or much to purpoſe. Both nature and education haue bred in me another hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, that I had rather reade or writ that which may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informe my underſtanding, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which may tickle my affection. In theſe things I conceiue the Heathen ſaid wel, that Nature is the beſt guide. For he that ſetteth him ſelfe to that, to which he hath no fitneſſe by nature: doth like him that ſwimmeth againſt the ſtreame, who being not able to hold out, is either driuen back or drowned.</p>
            <p>What meaneth all this? may ſome man ſay. Nothing elſe but this, that I may the eaſier be excuſed for follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that courſe, to which I find my ſelfe inclined, rather then that, which of it ſelfe might procure better liking. And this I truſt, I ſhall the ſooner obtaine by ſignifiyng, that my breeding ſtrengthened my inclination. For it pleaſed God, that at my firſt comming to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I ſhould be entred into the Kings-colledge, by that worthy and learned gentleman <hi>Sir William T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple,</hi> who in his <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke</hi> readings, alwayes laboured more to fitt vs, for the true uſe of that Art, then for vaine and idle ſpeculations, and earneſt wranglings about trifles of no profit nor cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty. Thus haue you the reaſon of my choyſe: may it pleaſe you to take knowledge alſo of the neceſſitie of this courſe.</p>
            <p>Cuſtome is ſaid to be an other nature; and is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a tyrant: becauſe many times it inforceth a man to that of which in his owne diſpoſition he hath no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liking. As I was brought up rather to the profitable uſe then vaine oftentation of that noble Art of <hi>Logicke:</hi> ſo (as new veſſels doe) keeping a tang of the firſt liquot,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21008:7"/> wherewith I was ſeaſoned, I applyed my ſelfe in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Philoſophy, Hiſtory, Oratory, Poetry, to make uſe of that Inſtrument of inſtruments, as <hi>(Ariſtotle</hi> calleth it,) in every peece of worke I undertooke. By this meanes it came to paſſe, that I began to thinke, (as men commonly doe account highly of that, wherewith they are moſt in loue) that <hi>Logicke</hi> was if not the onely, yet the principall Art, for the obtaining of true knowledge in any kind of learning whatſoever. If I lighted in reading upon any thing that was hard, that I ſeemed to be in a Labyrinth, <hi>Logicke</hi> was like <hi>Ariadnes</hi> clew of thrid, to guid me in it &amp; to bring me out of it. Was I deſirous in any exerciſe of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to take the right courſe in ſpeaking or writting? <hi>Logicke,</hi> like <hi>Mercuries Statue</hi> poynted me out the way, and ſhewed me all the turnings and windings in it. To conclude, my continuall practiſe in this Art, hath given it ſuch power over me, that with the Hebrew ſervant, my <note place="margin">Exod. 21. 6.</note> eare is faſt nayled to the doro poſt, ſo that I can nether ſtir from it, nor willingly heare any ſound without, that may draw me from thinking on it. This is the firſt degree of necoſſitie by which I am bound to this kind of writing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The other is greater and ſtreighter. And therein, as we are all ready, like our firſt parents to excuſe our faults, I haue a good mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to make a vertue of neceſſitie, by perſwading my ſelfe, that I doe that out of iudgement, which I doe indeed to help my weaknes, in judging. For I muſt and doe freely confeſſe, that I haue neither ſuch quicknes in apprehending, nor ſuch ſharpnes in judging, but that I find my ſelfe many times at a ſtand in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and at a loſſe in reſolving. What help haue I in this caſe, but to flee to <hi>Logicke</hi> as to an Oracle. By that I am inſtructed to take the frame in ſunder, to view every part by it ſelfe; to trie how every tenant and mortuis is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each to other, which principals are too weake, which peeces are too long, which too ſhort, whether they will ſerue in that building or no? if they will, how they muſt he ordered. If any man be able without this labour, at the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21008:7"/> firſt ſight of a building, to ſay all is right &amp; well, I would intreate him to beare with my ſlownes and backwardnes, upon promiſe, that I will not repine at his quicknes and forwardnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> As for them that thinke I troble my ſelfe more then needeth by taking this paines, I hope they are not like him in <hi>Seneca</hi> (as I remember <hi>Mendyrides)</hi> who would yawne and ſtretch, when he ſaw an other man labour, as if he had ben wearied therewith himſelfe. Long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aboue 40 yeare, hath made me fearefull &amp; ſuſpicious. I haue many times perſwaded my ſelfe of the ſtrength &amp; goodnes of an argument, which upon triall I haue found to be weake and naught. Many times I haue thought I underſtood a thing at the firſt reading very fully, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in upon the review I perceived I was deceived, In this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation it had not ben poſſible for me to haue diſcerned the weaknes and ſophiſtry of the Papiſts arguments, if I had not brought them to the beame, and weighed them parcell by parcell as I haue done. But if I had now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne to runne this courſe, and written more plauſibly to euery mans apprehenſion, yet I muſt haue been faine to come to it hereafter, whenſoeuer the aduerſaries ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay to make good their arguments againſt my anſwers. If this courſe be followed in examining Popiſh bookes, we ſhall ſaue them and our ſelues a great deale of labour: for they will be afraid to come to ſuch a triall, as will not ſuffer them to run the wild-gooſe chaſe, but will tether them, that they ſhall be kept within compaſſe, as if they were coiured within a circle; By this ſifting we ſhal ſeuer the flower from the bran, that a buſhell will be brought within a peck: that in a book of twentie ſheets, there will be no more to be anſwered, then may well be contained in fiue or ſixe.</p>
            <p>But this courſe will be too hard for ordinarie mens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings: it will, till they be acquainted with all, as ſtrange things commonly vſe to be: perhaps they will not at the firſt be able to conceiue fully of euery anſwer:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21008:8"/> if they will but take the paines to pauſe vpon it, they may learne more by a few lines often read, then by a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie once poſted ouer; beſides if they vnderſtand not all: yet I dare vndertake, they ſhall by this courſe vnderſtand more, and more certainely in reading 3 leaues, then by iunning ouer 13 in a looſe diſcourſe. Logicke (beloued,) is nothing elſe but the perfection of reaſon: it is not a deuiſe of Schollers, but a plant of nature: euery man vſeth it dayly in his ſpeaking or writing: the termes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne; ſo are the termes of warre, of Nauigation, of husbandrie, and of the meaneſt trade and occupation: till they be knowne they are hard, when they are known eaſie. If I might find ſo much fauour with you, as to get you to make a tryall, I make no doubt but this courſe would ſoone haue entertainment, and your knowledge thereby grow beyond your expectation.</p>
            <p>At the leaſt, let me craue and obtaine pardon of you for making ſo bold with you, in a matter (as I take it) ſo fit and needfull. I hope it ſhall not fall out with vs (reuerend fathers and brethren in the miniſtrie) as it did with <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> and <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> they were both <hi>Platoes</hi> Schollers: but followed diuers profeſſions: the one giuing himſelfe to Philoſophie, the other to Oratorie: each of them was ſo carried away with the pleaſure he took in his own courſe, that he wholy deſpiſed the other. As it becommeth me, I leaue euery one to his owne iudgement and practiſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be directed and aduiſed by any man, that can and will doe it. At ſome of you I wonder with delight, other I commend: there is none but I excuſe, as I deſire to be excuſed my ſelfe. Great wits may make a ſhift without artificiall Logicke: ordinary men ſhall find extraordinary helpe by it. The Lord in mercie ſo direct vs all, that we may ſeeke and procure by his bleſſing, the manifeſting and maintaining of his truth, to the glorie of his name, the good of his Church, and our euerlaſting ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21008:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the ſtate of the queſtion to be diſputed.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Heathen taught by <hi>Plato,</hi> alwayes held them for bad common-wealths men, who in a ciuill broile, when their countrie was in an vproare, would not labour to informe themſelues whether part had the right, and ioyne with them, but keepe aloofe from both, that they might ſtrike in with the conquerour to their moſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And what kinde of Chriſtians ſhall we account thoſe men, that ſeeing all on fire euer ſince they were borne about matter of Religion, haue not all their life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued what is true, what falſe, but are ſtill to make their choyſe whon they are neerer their buriall then their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? May we not iuſtly ranke them with thoſe luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme <note place="margin">Revel. 3. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> that were neither hot nor cold, fiſh nor fleſh? And may not they certainely looke for the euent which our Lord Ieſus threatneth, that he will ſpue them out of his mouth? It is high time therefore for all men <note place="margin">1. Reg. 18. 21.</note> to reſolue themſelues, whether they will follow God or <hi>Baal,</hi> Chriſt or Antichriſt, and not to continue halting betwixt two opinions.</p>
            <p>I cannot reaſonably conceiue whence this want of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution ſhould proceed, in them that are not deſperately careleſſe, or profainely politicke, but onely from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, of the neceſſity of being ſeparated from the church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The clouds of this ignorance I deſire and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſcatter by the light of truth, that all men, which will not ſhut their eyes againſt the beames thereof, may ſee both the way wherein they are, and the place it leades them too. Now, to the end I may the bettor vnderſtand my ſelfe, and be vnderſtood by them that ſeeke for reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if they doubt, or confirmation if they be reſolued; I will labour to ſpeak as plaine as the matter will giue me
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21008:9"/> leaue to doe, deſiring to haue that I deliuer rather iudged of, thèn wondered at. And becauſe we are accuſed by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſometimes of hereſie, ſometimes of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, I will apply my diſputation and diſcourſe to the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of our forefathers in ſeparating from the popiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and our ſelues in continuing that ſeparation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Wherefore that we may proceed orderly and plainely, I propound the matter to be diſputed in theſe termes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery man is bound vpon paine of damnation, to refuſe the faith of the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This propoſition or ſentence hath two things in it to be proued; That 1. The faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be refuſed. That 2. It is to be refuſed vpon paine of damnation. Theſe two I will handle ſeuerally. Firſt, by ſhewing the neceſſitie of that refuſall; Secondly, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the penaltie if that faith be not refuſed. And that nothing may be wanting, which may helpe the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt to conceiue and iudge aright of that which ſhall be ſpoken, (before I come to debate the point) I will declare the meaning of the termes in which I haue deliuered it, as ſhortly as I can with plaineneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> By the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I meane the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the ſaid Church deliuered by it in certaine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, propoſitions or ſentences, to be beleeued by all men that deſire to be ſaued as matters reuealed by God to that end. This their faith I conſider, as one individuall or ſingular thing. For although it may indeed be devided into many ſeuerall Articles, of which it conſiſts, and is as it were compacted or framed; yet it is conceiued by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as one intire body: becauſe they are all knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſame bond, namely by being aſſented to, or beleeued vpon one and the ſame ground or reaſon, which is the ſpirit of that body: and are all to be receiued a like vnder paine of the ſame <hi>Auathema</hi> or curſe, if they be not receiued: and this is eſpecially to be obſerued, as the maine point in this iuquir.</p>
            <p>That the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21008:9"/> of, it appeareth manifeſtly by Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites <note place="margin">Mr. Fiſher. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſe of ſaith, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of AD.</note> treatiſe of Faith, vnder the name of <hi>A. D.</hi> wherein the whole fourth chapter is ſpent to ſhew that Faith muſt be intire. <hi>Faith</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>muſt be intire, whole and ſound in all points: and it is not ſufficient to beleeue ſtedfaſtly ſome points, miſ-beleeuing, or not beleeuing obſtinately other ſome, or any one.</hi> The reaſon thereof followes a little after, where he ſaith, that <hi>Not to beleeue any one point whatſoeuer, which God by reualing it, doth teſtiſie to bo true, and which by his Church he hath commanded vs to beleeue, muſt needs be damnable; as being a not able iniury to Gods verity, and a great diſobedience to his will.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe writes the titular Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> that <hi>All Articles of faith determined by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Spalato Conſil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pag 20.</note> 
               <hi>the Church are fundamentall, and that none of them may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied without hereſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By this it comes to paſſe, that whoſoeuer is a true member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt as ſtedfaſtly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely beleeue the leaſt point of reliques, and Images deliuered by the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> as the greateſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the God-head, the Trinitie, the Redomption of the world by the Lord Ieſus, and that if he denie any of the former, he is no leſſe an hereticke, then if he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to beleeue any of the latter: yea, though he beleeue all they propound to be beleeued, ſaue ſome one ſmall matter, he is, for want of beleeuing that one, (if he know the Church propounds it to be beleeued) a miſcreant, and miſ-beleeuer; the reaſon of this is, that if the Church may erre in one thing, it may erre in an other, and ſo can be no ſure foundation of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> But what is it to refuſe the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> ſurely nothing elſe, but not to acknowledge the doctrine deliuered by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be true: but to abhoire it as falſe; I ſpeake not of euery particuler point, but of all ioyntly together, according to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer expoſition. For I doe freely and willingly confeſſe, that the Papiſts hold many great miſteries of diuinitie truely and ſoundly, wherein alſo we agree with them;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21008:10"/> but yet I ſay, we may not at any hand receiue their faith for true, as it is deliuered by them for one intire bodie of diuinitie, reuealed by God, to be acknowledged by all men that will be ſaued. So then to refuſe the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is not to beleeue that it is true: or to beleeue tht it is falſe; and this I ſay is required of euery man vpon paine of damnation. The expoſition of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point, vpon paine of damnation, I referre to the place where it is to be handled, after I haue diſpatched that which is firſt to be debated.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Authors that haue formerly hold the propoſition handled in this Treatiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THere are not a few that looke more after the man, then after the matter, and inquire rather who is the writer, then what is written. Therefore leaſt the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my condition and abilities, ſhould bring ſome preiudice to the truth I ſearch for, giue me leaue I pray you in the firſt place to ſhew, that the point I intend by Gods gracious aſſiſtance to proue, is no new conceit or deuiſe of mine, but a matter aduiſedly reſolued of, and ſet down by more then one of the worthies of our church and nation.</p>
            <p>Amongſt whom, the firſt in time and authoritie was that rare and pretious <hi>Iewel,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisburie. They</hi> 
               <note place="margin">B. Iewel deſ. apol. paro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cap, 22. diviſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>haue no cauſe</hi> (ſaith he of the Papiſts) <hi>to complaine of our departing, and to call vs againe to be fellowes and friends with them; If we ſhould content our ſelues to turne to the Pope, and to his errours, it ſhould be a very dangerous matter both to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Gods wrath againſt vs, and to clogge and condomne our ſoules for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in another place he ſpeakes thus to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21008:10"/> 
               <hi>As for vs, we haue not fallen from the Biſhop of Rome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">cap. 20. dirtſ: 2.</note> 
               <hi>vpon any matter of worldly reſpect: but ſo the caſe ſtood, that vnleſſe we left him, we could not come to Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> another ſhining light of the Vniuerſitie <note place="margin">D. Renolds.</note> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſhewes vs the ſame truth in another maner; viz. in his verſes vpon the third concluſion, handled in the Schooles Nouemb. 3. 1579.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If that ye ſeeke eternall life, ſee that you Rome forſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the ſame minde was Dr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> a man for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whether we reſpect reading or iudgement, knowne and approued of the Churches of Chriſt, eſpecially this of England. <hi>We ſay,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Church of Rome muſt be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. whitaker, de Eccleſ. cont. qu. 6 cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>forſaken of all men that deſire to be ſaued.</hi> And a little after he addes, that <hi>There can be no ſaluation hoped for in the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtlie Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> in knowledge and zeale a worthy Scholler of ſo excellent a Maſter, treading in his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps concludes: that <hi>All thoſe that will be ſaued, muſt depart</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rlins Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Chath. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the prolog ſed. Thus then</note> 
               <hi>and ſeparate themſelues from the faith and religion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue ſeene the iudgement of theſe learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Diuines, and therein the conſent of both the Vniuerſities <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford;</hi> for their bookes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the three laſt, were allowed for printing by the principall Doctors of the ſeuerall Vniuerſities then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in them; neither is it to be taken for the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Vniuerſities onely: but alſo of the whole Church: as appeareth euidently by the continuance of it from time to time, in the writings of theſe famous lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men ſucceſſiuely one after another. It was firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by that reuerend Father in defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to iuſtifie our departure from that ſtrumpet of Babylon; diuers yeares after proclaimed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in the publike Schooles by Dr. <hi>Reynolds;</hi> ratified afterwards by Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> in his publike lectures of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie; and laſt of all confirmed by Mr. <hi>Perkins:</hi> and by euerie one of theſe publiſhed in print, with the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21008:11"/> of our Church and State.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And this (to ſay the truth) hath alwayes beene the iudgement and practiſe of the Churches of God in all Proteſtant Countries, euer ſince the laſt birth and infancy of reformation in this age, for the ſpace of more then an hundred yeares; for what elſe hath beene aymed at in ſo many writings and diſputations of Ptoteſtants, but the iuſtifiing of our depar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure from the Synagogue of <hi>Rome; Not of a bodily departure</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Perkins) in reſpect of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Peform chathol. in Prol gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and preſence, but of a ſpiritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all ſeparation in reſpect of faith and religion.</hi> It cannot then reaſonly be denyed or doubted, but that our Church generally, holds ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a matter of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, yea of abſolute neceſſitie: eſpecially if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menber, that euery Pariſh throughout the whole Land is enioyned to haue the Booke of Biſhop <hi>Iewel,</hi> with the reſt of his workes in their ſeuerall Churches, for all men to read, and that they were all new printed to that end.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>wherein the neceſsitie of ſeparating is proued.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>YOu ſee from whom I take the point that I haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to maintaine: from the ſame men will I ferch the grounds of my diſputation. What is the reaſon by which theſe worthy, learned, and godly diuines did iuſtifie the ſeparation of our Church, and her continuing ſeparated from the Romiſh faith? let vs heare themſelues ſpeake: <hi>We haue departed from that Church</hi> (ſaith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father B. <hi>Iewel) whoſe erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs were proued and made</hi> 
               <note place="margin">B. Iewel Iuf. apol pag. 4. cap. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> 
               <hi>manifeſt to the world, which Church alſo had alreadie depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Gods word: and yet we haue not departed ſo much from it ſelfe, as from the errours thereof.</hi> What errours? They are generally implo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yed in theſe words of his: chap. 10.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21008:11"/> diuiſ. 2. <hi>Ignorance, errour, ſuperſtition, idolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, and the ſame commonly diſagreeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Scriptures.</hi> And againe: <hi>Theſe men haue broke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in peeces</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apolog. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5. cap 13. diviſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>all the pipes and conduites: they haue ſtopped all the ſprings, and choaked vp the fonntaine of liuing water with dirt and mire.</hi> And againe: <hi>Wee haue renounced that Church wherein vve</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cap. 15. diviſ. 2. Apol.</note> 
               <hi>could neither haue the word of God ſincerely taught, nor the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred, nor the nam: of God duely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon: and wherein was nothing able to ſtay any wiſe man, or one that hath conſideration of his owne ſaſetie. To conclude, vve</hi> 
               <note place="margin">part 6. chap. 22. diviſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>haue departed from him</hi> (ſaith that learned B. of the Pope) <hi>who hath vtterly forſaken the Catholicke faith.</hi> For (as Dr. <note place="margin">Bilſon Dialogue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t 3.</note> 
               <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſaith moſt truely) <hi>No Article of the Church of Rome, wherein we diſſent from them is Catholicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>D. Reynolds</hi> ſpeakes not ſo plaine, yet giues us ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to underſtand, that he therefore concluded the Church of Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e was to be forſaken, becauſe ſhe was no ſound member of the Catholicke Church, nor held the right faith. Her unſoundnes he thus ſets out. <hi>The Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reynolds conclu. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of Rome is not diſtempered with a little ague, ſuch as hindreth not the functions of life greatly; but is ſicke of a canker, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>proſy, or rather of a peſtilence, in ſo much that ſhe is paſt hope of recouery, unleſſe our Saviour Chriſt the heavenly phyſician doe giue her wholeſome medicines to purge her of perm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious humors.</hi> Concluſ: 5.</p>
            <p>And in his preſace to his ſixe concluſions? he writes thus. <hi>Sith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the fellowſhip of the Church of Rome it was not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Preface, at the 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> 
               <hi>lawfull for vs, either to ſerue God with a holy worſhip, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue God with a holy faith, as God hath commanded: ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h the Church of Rome being taken with contagious diſeaſes and a frenſie, did put her Counſellers to the fire, friends to the ſword, brethren to cruell death, and ſtained the faith of Chriſt with reproaches, creatures with the Lords honour, Gods ſervice with Idolatry: we went away from Papiſts, not willingly as from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n; not vnwillingly as from heritickes.</hi> But <hi>D. Whitaker,</hi> and <hi>M.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o 2. quiſt. 6. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Perkins</hi> are moſt plaine. <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (ſaith D. Whitaker) <hi>that the Church of Rome is to be ſhuned of all men, and that <hi>no</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21008:12"/> ſalvation is to be hoped for in it; yea we ſay it is to be cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed as a deepe pitt of hereſy and errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Perkins</hi> avoucheth our departure for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <note place="margin">Perkins in prolog. Reſor. Catho.</note> 
               <hi>The cauſe of this Separation lyeth in the Church of Rome, namely the cup of abomination in the whores hand, which is their haereticall and ſchiſmaticall religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Vpon this foundation of theſe learned men, I ſet this frame of diſputation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Euery erroneous faith is to be refuſed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The faith of the Church of Rome is an erroneous faith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therefore the faith of the Church of Rome is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Can there be any queſtion made of the firſt part or propoſition of this reaſon, when the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iude</hi> exhorts all men without exception of perſon, time or matter, <hi>to ſtriue for the faith delivered to the Saints?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudev. 3.</note> But how ſtriue we for that faith which is the reuealed truth of God, if we can be content to beleeue errours which are againſt the truth? Yea, what doe we elſe by holding errours for truth, but adde to the diuine reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation giuen by the Lord God himſelfe, contrary to his charge? Deut. 4. 2. <hi>You ſhall put nothing to the word that I command you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond part which we call the aſſumption or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, <note place="margin">Deutr. 4. 2.</note> is that wherein all the doubt lieth: for what is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the worſe, for granting that an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous faith is to be refuſed, vnles their faith can be proued erroneous. And whereas I ſay in my queſtion and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation erroneous, rather then hereticall, I doe it od of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, becauſe I would ſhunne all needleſſe wrangling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the word: for it ſeemes to many ſomewhat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what is properly to be called hereſy; For my part I can not ſee that any falſe propoſition deliuered for an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of faith, can be leſſe then hereſie: I doubt not but a man may thinke ſomthing to be true which is falſe, &amp; be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21008:12"/> no heriticke: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall obſtinately hold ſuch a point for an Article of faith, neceſſarily to be beleeued by all men vpon paine of damnation, cannot for ought I ſee, be freed from hereſie. As for the errours of the Papiſts, Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> Dr. <hi>Whitakers,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> (as we haue ſeene,) make no doubt to call them hereſies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Now that we may the better vnderſtand whether the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be erroneous or no, we muſt enquire how the truth and falſeneſſe of faith is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned: which we cannot doe either better or otherwiſe, then by conſidering how the Article of faith, or propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition enioyned to be beleeued, agreeth with the diuine teſtimonie concerning that point or Article; for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine teſtimonie is the thing or rule, to which the Article muſt be applied, and by which it muſt be ſquared; ſo that if it agree wholy with it, it is true: if in any part it differ from that teſtimonie, it is falſe and erroneous. This <note place="margin">Seſſ. 14. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Decret de neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſatiffactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n is Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram paenitentiae can. 6.</note> deſcription of errour and falſehood in matters of faith, is warranted by the Councell of Trent, where they make falſehood conſiſt in differing from the word of God: and <hi>That which differs from the inſtitution of Chriſt, is called an humane tradition, and therefore is erroneous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> According to this declaration of a falſe and erroneous faith, I proceed now to ſhew, that the faith of the Church of Rome is falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>That faith which hath a falſe and ertoneous foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>Wherein firſt I take it for granted, that Faith muſt haue an extrinſecall foundation out of the shings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felues which are to be beleeved. This outward and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall foundation is the credit and authority of him, that delivereth thoſe things for true, and requires aſſent or agrement to them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I hold it for certaine, and agrred vpon by all, that faith is true or falſe, according to the foundation whereon it ſtands: as the diuine reſtimonie begets a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine faith, an humane teſtimonie breeds an humane,
<pb facs="tcp:21008:13"/> which may thus appeare. What makes the faith of the ancient heathen, and the now heatheniſh Turks, and all ſorts of Infidels, who beleeue that there is but one God, to be humane falſe and erroneous; and the faith of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians concerning the ſame point, to be diuine and true: but the diuerſe foundations of theſe faiths, the former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon the coniectures and teſtimonies of men: the other ariſing out of the witneſſe of God himſelfe. To come nearer home; why doe the Papiſts denie that wee are of their faith, although they confeſſe wee hold the very ſame Articles of the Creed that they profeſſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree with them in moſt points of religion: but for that we haue not the ſame foundation of our faith, which they haue of theirs? It is then the goodneſſe or badneſſe of the foundation that make the faith good or bad: ſo that where the foundation is falſe, the faith whatſoeuer it be cannot be true.</p>
            <p>The propoſition thus prooued, I will adde the aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it: The foundation of the faith of the Church of Rome is falſe and erroneous: For the foundation of their faith, is the authority of the Paſtors of their Church, as it <note place="margin">Sect. 4. <hi>Decret. de edit. ſcriptur. ſect. praeterea.</hi>
               </note> is manifeſt by the Councell of Trent: <hi>It is the office of the Church</hi> (ſaith the Councel) <hi>to giue ſentence of the true meaning and ſenſe of the Scriptures.</hi> Now by the Church, they meane the Paſtours of the Church, as their continuall practiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, no man being ſuffered to giue a voice in any Councell, but their Biſhops, whom onely they hold to be the Paſtours of the Church. By true ſenſe and meaning they vnderſtand the doctrine of faith, which is nothing elſe but the Word of God, truly vnderſtood. By the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they meane euery particular place of Scripture; for, if they ſhould meane ſome places onely, there could be no certainty in this their decree, vnleſſe they had determined, what particular places they are, whereof the Church may giue ſentence.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus declared, I diſpute thus:</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21008:13"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> They that haue the office to determine which is the true faith, their authority is the foundation of Faith.</p>
            <p>But the Church hath the office to determine which is the true faith: as it appeares by the words of the Councell ere-while recited.</p>
            <p>Therfore the authority of the Church is the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their faith.</p>
            <p>That the Church of Rome claimes this authority, it may further appeare by thoſe titles whcih it vſurpeth in the ſaid Councell, that, <hi>The Biſhop of Rome is Gods <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Seſſ. 6. de refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. cap. 1. &amp; Seſſ. 14. de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia. cap. 7. Seſſ. 7. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. Can. 3. &amp; Seſſ. 22. de ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio miſſae cap. 8 De verbo dei lib. 3. cap. 3. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. Tota igitur. Cap. 5. Sect. Ex his.</note> 
               <hi>earth. The Church of Rome is the mother and miſtris of all Churches.</hi> Yea, euerie man may plainly ſee, that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> teacheth the ſame things of the church of Rome. <hi>The Church is the iudge of the true ſenſe of the Scripture, and all controuerſies.</hi> By Church, hee vnderſtands the Pope with a Councell: and this, he ſaith, is expreſly to be found in the Councell of Trent, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4. which is the place I alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ere-while. <hi>It is committed ſingularly to Peter and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, that they ſhould teach all men what is to bee held concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the doctrine of faith.</hi> For the expounding whereof, he ſaith a little after, <hi>Sect. Si etiam;</hi> that, <hi>The Lord ſpeakes of a ſingular office of teaching the whol Church, by appointing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing what is to be beleeued of all men.</hi> And againe, he ſaith; that <hi>The Councels, &amp; Popes execute the office of a Iudge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cap. 10. Sect. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond. aliud eſt.</note> 
               <hi>to them by God.</hi> What the Office of a Iudge is, he ſhews in the ſame place a few lines before: <hi>To explication after the manner of a Iudge, there is authoritie required: A Iudge deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth his ſentence, as a thing that neceſſarily muſt be followed.</hi> To conclude, hee tells vs in the ſame tenth chapter; that, <note place="margin">Sect. Septi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um argumentum.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtians, who are ſure the Church cannot erre in expounding the doctrine of faith, are bound to receiue that doctrine, and not to doubt whether thoſe things be ſo or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This matter <hi>Bellarmine</hi> makes plaine to all men, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of this Office, in this ſort; <hi>The Scripture for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cap. 10. Sect. Reſponde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus.</note> 
               <hi>It ſelfe needs not the witnes of men, for it is moſt true in it ſelfe, whether it be vnderſtood, or not: but for our ſake it needs the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Church, becauſe otherwiſe wee are not certaine, what</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21008:14"/> 
               <hi>bookes are ſacred and diuine, nor what is the true and proper mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> In the ſame Chapter he giues vs to vnderſtand, what manner of foundation the teſtimony of the church is. <hi>The word of God deliuered by the Prophets and Apoſtles, is the firſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sect. Reſpondeo, Ad hoc.</note> 
               <hi>foundation of our faith, for, therefore we beleeue whatſoeuer we beleeue, becauſe God hath reuealed it by his Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But we adde, that beſides this firſt foundation, there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſecondary foundation needfull, to wit, the teſtimony of the Church: for, we know not certainly what God hath reuealed but by the teſtimony of the Church. Therefore our faith cleaueth to Chriſt, the firſt truth, reuealing thoſe myſteries, as to the firſt foundation: It cleaues alſo to Peter, that is, to the Pope, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and expounding theſe myſteries, as to a ſecondary foundation.</hi> And to make the matter yet more plaine, he ſpeakes thus in the ſame tenth chap. <hi>Sect. Reſpondeo, verbum. We are to know,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sect. Reſponde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, verbum.</note> 
               <hi>that a Propoſition or article of faith is concluded in ſuch a Syllogiſme as this.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer God hath reuealed in the Scriptures is true.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But this God hath reuealed in the Scriptures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therefore this is true.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the firſt of theſe Propoſitions no man makes any queſtion. The ſecond is held for certaine truth amongst all Catholikes, for, it is grounded vpon the teſtimony of the Church, that is, the Councell, or the Pope.</hi> By which it appeares, how little M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Fiſher</hi> vnderſtands the doctrine whereof he makes profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or how vnaduiſedly he deliuereth his opinion. For, whereas <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will haue a two-fold foundation, prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſecondary, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Fiſher</hi> will acknowledge but one, namely; the authority of God, ſpeaking by the mouth of the church: <hi>Chriſtian beleefe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ought onely to bee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Treat. of Faith in the Preface. <hi>Sect</hi> of which point.</note> 
               <hi>grounded vpon the authority of God, ſpeaking by the mouth of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> We haue ſeene <hi>Bellarmines</hi> opinion of this matter: which indeed agrees very well with the words of the Councell, where it challengeth the office of interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For, in that clayme it preſumes, that the diuine truth is already reuealed, and that it is the firſt foundation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21008:14"/> of our faith; to which the office of the Church is added, which is but a ſecondary foundation. Now, by theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Counce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> it is cleare, that;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The foundation of the Romiſh faith, is the authority of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This foundation of faith (ſay wee) is falſe and erroneous: That our Sauiour Chriſt and his Prophets and Apoſtles are the foundation of faith, wee beleeue and acknowledge, and in this we and they agree. That ſecondary foundation which lyeth in the authority and teſtimony of the church, we refuſe as falſe and naught, and in this lyeth the true dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt vs and them in this point: as beſides other, <note place="margin">De Script. quaeſt. 5. cap. 3. Apol. part. 2. chap. 3. diuiſ. 2. 11</note> D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Whitaker</hi> hath noted, and the reuerend B. <hi>Iewell.</hi> And this indeed is the main reaſon why we may not ioyn with them.</p>
            <p>If they demand of vs, VVhy we receiue not this autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the church, for a foundation of faith? VVe anſwer; Becauſe we find no commiſſion in the word of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any ſuch office is conueyed vnto it. Neither deale wee herein any otherwiſe then reaſon and law direct men to do in the like caſe. For, is any man ſo deſtitute of reaſon, or ſo ignorant of the law, that he would receiue a man for L. Chancellour, L. Treaſurer, or Lord Chiefe Iuſtice, that were not able to ſhew any commiſſion for the hauing and executing ſuch an office? And ſhall wee in a buſineſſe of ſuch importance, that concernes our free-hold, not onely for our preſent being of the church, but for our future be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming heires of glory in heauen, giue credit to men vpon their bare word, without ſight of their commiſſion? VVerfore doth our Lord and Sauiour ſo often in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, plead his authority from God, warranted by the old Teſtament: and vpbraid the Iewes with lightneſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for being ready to receiue one that ſhould come in his owne name? If then the Papiſts would haue vs beleeue, that their church is appointed to bee a foundation, let them ſhew their warrant for it, and we will accept it, and build our faith vpon it.</p>
            <p>But we looke that their commiſſion ſhould be very plain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21008:15"/> and certaine, becauſe it is of ſuch a matter as no naturall reaſon can conceiue to be true. For who would imagine or beleeue that the Apoſtles, who had a little before receiued full power of order and iuriſdiction ioyntly and equally with <hi>Peter,</hi> (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth) ſhould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly <note place="margin">De Rom. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. lib. 1. cap. 12. Sect. vt autem.</note> haue their authority abridged, and be made ſubiect to <hi>Peter:</hi> yea, to his ſucceſſors too, as it fell out with S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> to learne of them which wee bookes of Scripture, and what was the meaning of the ſeuerall places or texts; and what was true, what falſe in Diuinity.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the matter it ſelfe is of ſuch importance, by their doctrine, that without the conſtant beliefe thereof, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience according thereto, there is no poſſibility of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For, <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine) will not be ſed by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De verb. Dei. lib 3. cap. 5. Sect. quartum.</note> 
               <hi>that is, learne of him or his ſucceſſors as iudges and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners, what he is to take for matter of faith, and what is the ſenſe of the Scripture, is none of Chriſts ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the courſe that is to be followed in this diſputation.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I Haue ſhewed that the foundation of the ſaith of the Church of Rome, is the authority and teſtimony of the church; and haue refuſed that foundation as vnſound and erroneous. It will now perhaps be looked for, that I ſhould proceed by prouing that it is falſe and counterfeit. But I ſee no neceſſary or ſufficient reaſon for this courſe, and therefore haue rather choſen to follow tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, which the matter it ſelfe leads me to, and in which it leads me.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The queſtion betwixt the church of Rome and vs is this: Whether the articles or propoſitions to which they require our aſſent, as to certaine truths, reuealed by God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him to be beleeued vpon perill of damnation if we do not aſſent and beleeue, be reuealed and commanded
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21008:15"/> by God, or no, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe putteth it in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of his Syll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>giſme, ſet down by me Chap. 3. num. 9. The church of Rome ſaith they are, and call for obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereto accordingly. We deny that they are reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and enioyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by God, and therefore refuſe to giue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them. Who ſeeth not that the very nature of this difference betwixt vs, layeth vpon them a neceſſity of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that thoſe points or articles are propounded by God, to be beleeued as matters of faith reuealed by him?</p>
            <p>This made the reuerend and learned B. <hi>Iewell,</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, <note place="margin">3 B. Iewell Apol. part. 1. chap. 10. diuiſ. 1.</note> tell the Doctors of the Romiſh church: that, <hi>It was their part to prooue clearly and truly, that the Romiſh Church is the true and right inſtructed Church of God.</hi> And in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Cole,</hi> lett. <hi>D D. E E.</hi> to affirme: that, <hi>It was vnreaſonable for that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, to call for the proofes of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> And therefore as it appeares in that anſwer, lett. <hi>O.</hi> he ſtands vpon the negatiue (as he ſpeakes) and putteth the Papiſts to their proofes, becauſe they preſſe vs to receiue thoſe points for articles of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> This courſe I haue holden in thoſe bookes that I haue formerly publiſhed in this kind of writing, this I meane to hold now and hereafter, if it pleaſe God to afford me op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to goe forward in the defence of his truth. Yet for their better ſatisfaction, and clearer manifeſting of the truth, I will alwaies giue ſome reaſon of my denying the propoſitions I refuſe: howſoeuer, it were enough for an anſwer, to deny that which of it ſelfe is not apparantly true. And thus much of the courſe of this diſputation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I returne now to the diſputation it ſelfe. The maine ground for the proofe of the authority of the church in this kind, is taken by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> out of <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15, 16, 17. <note place="margin">Ioh. 21. 15, 16. <hi>De verbo dei. lib. 3. cap. 5. Sect. quartum teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, &amp; ſeqq.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ieſus ſaid to Simon Peter, Simon the ſonne of Ionas, loueſt thou mee more then theſe? He ſaid, yea Lord, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. He ſaid vnto him, Feed my ſheepe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe words <hi>Bellarmine</hi> diſputeth thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feeding of Chriſts ſheepe,</hi> Ioh. 21. 15. <hi>is a ſingular office of teaching the whole Church, by determining and iudging</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21008:16"/> 
               <hi>what is to bee beleeued of all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Peter and his ſucceſſours the feeding of Chriſts ſheepe is committed.</hi> Ioh. 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore to Peter and his ſucceſſors, a ſingular office of teaching the whole Church, by iudging and determining what is to be beleeued of all men, is committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon this concluſion <hi>Bellarmine</hi> inferreth: that, <hi>he that will not be thus taught by Peter, is none of Christs ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Many weighty points are hudled vp together in this Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme, worthy of ſerious conſideration and debating. In the Propoſition, or firſt part, theſe foure things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>In thoſe words,</hi> Ioh. 21. 15. <hi>a ſingular Office is contained.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Feeding there, ſignifieth teaching.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Feeding Chriſts ſheepe is, teaching the whole Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Teaching the whole church is, by way of determining what is to be beleeued of all men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All theſe are contained in the Propoſition, and euery one of them ſo neceſſarily required to the truth thereof, that if any one of them bee vntrue, the Propoſition of neceſſity muſt be falſe. How then ſhall the concluſion be an article of faith, as the Papiſts will haue it? I will therfore examine euery one of them ſeuerally, and then goe forward to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the Aſſumption.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the two former points of the foure.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THE firſt of the foure points to be diſcuſſed is this: <hi>In the words rehearſed,</hi> Ioh. 21. 15. <hi>a ſingular office is appointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeakes of a ſingular Office, the words themſelues ſhew: that hee muſt needs bee vnderſtood of appointing ſuch an office, not of diſpoſing of one already appointed, it is manifeſt: as well becauſe there was no office
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21008:16"/> yet ordained, but that which was common to <hi>Peter</hi> with the reſt of the Apoſtles; and therefore not ſingular: as alſo for that it will not ſerue <hi>Bellarmines</hi> turne to ſpeake of an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice common to all the Apoſtles, ſince hee endeauors to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſuch an office vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> as was proper and peculiar to him, and ſuch as no other Apoſtle euer had. This may far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeare by another place in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> where he ſaith, that <hi>that very thing is really giuen</hi> Iohn 21. 15. <hi>which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,</hi> Mat 16. 19. <hi>I will giue thee the keyes of the Kingdome of heauen:</hi> and as he there ſaith, <hi>giuen to the ſame</hi> Simon, <hi>to whom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pont. lib. 1. cap. 14. Sect. Ac pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum &amp; cap. 12. Sect Et prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea.</note> 
               <hi>before it was promiſed:</hi> hee ſaith, that <hi>the keyes were promiſed</hi> Math. 16. 19. <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eliuered</hi> Iohn 21. 15, 16, 17. Thus haue we the firſt point in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> propoſition, now let vs try the truth of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For our parts we vtterly reiect it as falſe, becauſe wee are out of doubt, it cannot any way bee ſoundly proued. And we are the rather ſo perſwaded becauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath not once attempted to proue it; although hee could not choſe but ſee, that there was neceſſity of prouing it: for it is not ſo plaine and manifeſt in it ſelfe, that it needs no proofe; and the concluſion drawne out of it is an Article of their faith; yea ſuch an article, as, like <hi>Atlas,</hi> beareth the waight of the whole body of their faith. Beſides, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> knew well enough that we deny it to be true. For hee brings <hi>Luthers</hi> words to that purpoſe. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his booke <hi>de poteſtate Papae)</hi> affirmes that <hi>by the word Feed,</hi> Iohn 21. <hi>there is no new power giuen, but only the duty of louing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pont. la. ca. 15. Sect. Iam vero.</note> 
               <hi>and teaching enioyned</hi> Peter, <hi>who was made an Apoſtle before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Neither doth the text it ſelfe, nor any other place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (for ought they ſay, or we ſee) afford vs any proofe thereof. If there bee any thing in the text for their reliefe, it is in that <hi>Peter</hi> is commanded to feed. But this charge doth not ſo much as imply the appointing of an office: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe feeding is many times enioyned, where there is no ſingular office ordained, but the executing of an office com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, which had before been appointed. So the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter, 1. Peter</hi> 5. 2. chargeth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were already <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 2.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21008:17"/> Miniſters, to <hi>feed the flicke of God.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20. 28. giues the like charge to the Elders or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <note place="margin">Act. 10. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſus, Take heed to your ſelues, and to all the flocke, to feed the Church of God.</hi> And this Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art,</hi> Chap. 3. diuiſ. 2.</note> and vrged againſt <hi>Hart,</hi> You ſay true, wee might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with good reaſon refuſe this propoſition, till it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But I will deale more kindly with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and ſhew that <hi>Luther</hi> truely affirmed, there was no new office erected by thoſe words, but the execution of one formerly appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, enioyned.</p>
            <p>If this feeding be the teaching, for which all the Apoſtles had commiſſion, <hi>Mark. 16 15. Goe ye into all the world, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mark. 16. 15.</note> 
               <hi>preach the Gospell to euery creature:</hi> Iohn 20. 23. <hi>Whoſe ſinnes ſoeuer ye remit, they are remitted to them:</hi> then is it not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of a new office: for this was at our Sauiours third ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to his Diſciples, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 13. that, at his firſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. 19. <hi>Bellarm. de pont. Rom. lib. 1. cap. 12. Sect. Dices &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 19. 20. when (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirmeth) <hi>they had power giuen them both of iudiſdiction to gouerne, and of order to execute their ſacrificing Prieſthood.</hi> And it had beene a thing not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming our Sauiours wiſdome, to giue a new Commiſſion when there was no need, nor occaſion of ſo doing. Yea, to ſay the truth, it had beene altogether in vaine, becauſe the former being as ſufficient and in force, there could be no place for this later.</p>
            <p>But this feeding, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. 15. is the teaching, for which they had commiſſion <hi>Mark. 16. 15. Ioh.</hi> 20. 23. For wee finde no other kinde of feeding but this one practiſed by the Apoſtles in the new Teſtament, namely, feeding by way of reuealing. This appeareth touching the Scriptures, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. authorit lib 2. cap. 12. Sect. Obſeruandum, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Sect. Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>untur Counc. Trent. Seſſ. 4 decret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Canon. ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turatum.</hi>
               </note> 2. <hi>Tim. 4. 15. The Scriptures were giuen by inſpiration. 2. Pet. 1. 21. Holy men of God ſpake as they were moued by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo confeſſeth: <hi>The Scripture is the word of God immediatly reuealed. The holy writers had immediate reuelation, and writ the words of God.</hi> As for traditions, which the church of Rome makes a ſecond part of the diuine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, or word of God, by their owne confeſſion, they are alſo by reuelation, for ſo ſaith the Councell of Trent: <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb facs="tcp:21008:17"/> were either receiued by the Apostles, from the mouth of our Sauiour, or deliuered by themſelues, the holy Ghoſt enditing them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Indeed this <hi>feeding, Ioh.</hi> 21. 15. is nothing elſe but an exhortation or charge for the performance of that duty, which was enioyned in that Commiſſion, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 15. That it was ſuch an exhortation, the manner of deliuering the words ſheweth, which is, by repeating the ſame thing three ſeuerall times. For this courſe is very fit to make an impreſſion of a duty commanded, no way beſeeming the giuing of a Commiſſion Beſides, it anſwereth to <hi>Peters</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of his Maſter thrice: as <hi>Cyril</hi> noteth in <hi>Ioh. Becauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cyril ſupra Ioh. lib. 12. cap. 64.</note> 
               <hi>he denied him thrice at his paſſion, therefore there is a threefold confeſſion of loue required of him. A threefold confeſſion</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin) anſwereth to a threefold negation, that the tongue may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. Tract. in Ioh. 123.</note> 
               <hi>expreſſe as much loue, as it did feare.</hi> Adde hereunto, that our Lord calls for the performance of this duty, as a proofe of <hi>Peters</hi> loue to him, wherein hee had failed more then the reſt, becauſe he had made more proteſtation of it then the reſt. For thus lies the reaſon. If thou loue me as thou haſt profeſſed thou doeſt, ſhew thy loue by the performing of the duty of feeding. But what proofe had it beene of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> loue to our Sauiour, to become the viſible Monarch of the whole Church? Well might the giuing of ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice argue our Sauiours loue to <hi>Peter,</hi> but the taking it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, could not teſtifie any great loue of his to our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. For, who would haue refuſed ſuch an offer? The bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of teaching was laid vpon the other Apoſtles, as well as vpon him; the honour of the Supremacy (if this were true) was appropriated to him; yea, the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who before were equall to him, were now made infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour and ſubiect to him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, in giuing a commiſſion, the authority of him that giues is ordinarily expreſſed, alwaies implyed. <hi>Mat. 28. 18, 19. All power is giuen to me in heauen and earth: Goe therefore and teach all nations, Ioh. 20. 21, 22, 23. As my father ſent me, ſo ſend I you, receiue the holy Ghoſt: whoſe ſins, &amp;c.</hi> But here, although (as they ſay) it is the onely place that ſpeaks
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21008:18"/> of this commiſſion, there is no authority, either expreſſed or implyed: onely as <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was a duty of loue to feed, as it had beene formerly a proofe of feare to deny.</hi> What elſe then can this Feeding be, but the teaching, which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned all the Apoſtles at our Sauiours firſt appearing to them? Whereupon I may ſafely conclude, that the word neither neceſſarily, nor in any likelihood of reaſon impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the erection of any new office in the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Let vs now proceed to debate the ſecond point: yet with this memorandum, that although it be neuer ſo plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, yet <hi>Bellarmines</hi> propoſition of a new office appointed, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. 15. is falſe, becauſe the firſt point contained in it, of a ſingular office here ordained, is neither true nor likely. The thing now to be diſcuſſed, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feeding Chriſts ſheepe,</hi> Ioh. 21. 15. <hi>is teaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſentence is plainly deliuered by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in that propoſition, as he that looks vpon it cannot chooſe but ſee, and proued alſo by two reaſons: the former; that, <hi>Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſheepe are fed by teaching:</hi> the latter; that <hi>The Lord ſaith by Ieremy, I will giue you Paſtors according to my heart, which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall feed you with knowledge and vnderſtanding.</hi> But theſe proofes might haue been ſpared; for we acknowledge, that Feeding is Teaching.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> But for the fuller diſcuſsing of this matter, wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as we ſaw, chap. 4. numb. 9. tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs: <hi>Teaching is double: by reuealing, or propounding things reuealed.</hi> Wee ſay, that the teaching here ſpoken of, is by reuelation, not by propounding matters already reuealed, as they would haue it. But if they will haue vs yeeld to it, they muſt proue it, and not take it for granted, as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> doth. For, without it be proued, as I ſignified chap. 6. numb. 6. his propoſition cannot be true. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as eaſie and reaſonable for vs to refuſe his argument, grounded vpon that, which we deny, as for him to affirme that he cannot proue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Yet, that we may deale more kindly with him, then he doth with vs, wee will giue him a reaſon of our anſwer:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21008:18"/> which is, that, None of the Apoſtles did euer vſe any other kind of teaching, then reuealing. If they deny this, let them ſhew, that any Apoſtle did euer informe the Church, that, <hi>This or that booke was ſcripture:</hi> that, <hi>this or that tradition was by diuine authority:</hi> that, <hi>this or that place, had this or that ſenſe.</hi> And that this information of theirs, was not by way of reuelation: that is, of immediate inſpiration and motion from God: wherby they were freed from all errour. If they cannot doe this, as I am out of doubt they cannot, it muſt needs be granted, that they taught onely by reuelation, not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> They will perhaps obiect, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 7. but in vaine: For the Apoſtles doe not there expound any place of Scripture formerly written, or propound matters already reuealed by God: but by the immediate inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, reſolue and enioyne what was to be done in that caſe. So that their determination was a law then firſt giuen by way of reuelation from God, not by way of interpreting and propounding what the Lord had formerly deliuered. For it is manifeſt, that the Lord hath no where taught in the old Teſtament (&amp; the new was not then written) that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles conuerted to the faith, were to abſtain from ſtrangled things, and from blood: to the forbidding wherof, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt directed them immediately, vpon that occaſion, for that time. From which after a time he freed them by the like direction and reuelation giuen to the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and by him to the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. And that this decree of the Apoſtles was made by reuelation and inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Ghoſt, <note n="*" place="margin">De Rom. Pons. lib. 4. cap. 25. Sect. Reſponde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad primum.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe grants.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Yea, the Apoſtles in that ſame place ſeeme to take a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary courſe to that: which, if they had expounded the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Scriptures, or propounded things formerly deliuered, they muſt haue followed. For as it appeareth by debating of the point by <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> the old teſtament abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> freed the Gentiles conuerted from the ceremoniall law. <hi>Why tempt ye God,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> Verſ. 10.) <hi>to lay a yoake on the Diſciples neckes, which neither our fathers nor wee were able to</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21008:19"/> 
               <hi>beare?</hi> Yet the Apoſtles by this decree of theirs, bind them to part of that law, by enioyning them, Verſ. 20. 29. <hi>To obſtaine from blood, and that that is ſtrangled.</hi> Which they might not haue done, if they had propounded matters al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reſolued of, and not followed the immediate reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and direction of the holy Ghoſt. To this I may adde, the manner of this charge, giuen by the Apoſtles, which is by inſpiration from the holy Ghoſt, whoſe authority in this caſe they alledge, <hi>It ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt:</hi> not, <hi>thus ſaith Moſes, Dauid, or the Lord by this or that Prophet.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that Councel, the Apoſtles did reueale what was to be done, not propound what formerly had beene reuealed. And yet this is the onely place in all the new Teſtament, wherein there is any ſhew of Feeding by expounding and propounding, otherwiſe then by reuelation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the two latter points in</hi> Bellarmines <hi>Propoſitions.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> HAuing found the two former points to be light and falſe: I come now to weigh the third, which is ſet downe as plainly as either of the former: that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feeding Chriſts ſheepe,</hi> Ioh. 21. 15. <hi>is teaching the whole Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There hath beene enough ſaid already to diſcredit and diſable the propoſition: yet I will goe forward, that it may appeare what truth there is in it. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> laboureth <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. lib. 1. cap. 16.</note> much to proue, that by Chriſts Sheepe in this place, all Chriſtians whatſoeuer are ſignified. But what needeth all this adoe? Wee neuer meant to deny it, neither doth our granting, or his prouing of it, any thing at all helpe them, or hinder vs. For, there is nothing meant in this place by teaching, but reuealing, as I ſhewed in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chap. numb. 10, 11, 12. But this the church of Rome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21008:19"/> claimes not, but ſtriueth tooth and naile for ſuch a teaching as conſiſteth in expounding and propounding things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed: yea I will grant him both propoſition and aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the tearmes wherein they are deliuered. Becauſe the whole Church was to bee inſtructed by the feeding here ſpoken of, and no man had or hath liberty either to refuſe as vntrue, or not to obey as needleſſe any thing that ſhould be deliuered according to this commandement, <hi>Feed my ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The more doth <hi>Bellarmin</hi> wrong vs, in ſaying, that <hi>we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that the whole Church is meant by the name of ſheepe in this place.</hi> For whereas our Diuines ſay that <hi>Peter was made a particular not an vniuerſall Biſhop:</hi> they meane not thereby to deny his authority to teach all Nations whatſoeuer, and all congregations in all nations, as occaſion was offered, but onely to ſignifie, that hee had no commiſſion giuen by thoſe, or any other words to be ſoueraigne Biſhop of the whole Church, as they ſpeake in the words going a little <note place="margin">Sect. Primum.</note> before. As for that of <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15. they ſhew, that thoſe words can argue no ſuch authority, becauſe then <hi>Paul</hi> might not haue had the ſame office among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> had among the <hi>Iewes:</hi> ſo that the vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty denied in that, and other places by our Diuines, is an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of feeding thoſe, who were ioyned with him in the ſame commiſſion of feeding, and had equall authority with him to reueale the truth of God, to all the ſheepe of Chriſt without exception: which <hi>Caluin</hi> expreſſeth thus, <hi>If the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caluin. Inſtitut. lib. 4. c. 6. n. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſame authority be granted to all which was promiſed to one, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall he be aboue his fellowes in office?</hi> As for n. 7. which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> quoteth, <hi>Caluin</hi> doth neither mention nor ſignifie that place, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15. therein.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There remaineth the fourth poynt to be conſidered, that <hi>ſeeding Chriſts ſheepe,</hi> Iohn 21. 15. <hi>is teaching by way of iudging or determining what is to be beleeued of all men.</hi> This alſo is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in plaine termes, and is of as much importance, as any of the other three. His proofe is, that <hi>wee cannot better vnderſtand it then in that ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21008:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21008:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21008:21"/>
            <p>I ſee not, why I may not grant him this without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience. For indeed the Apoſtles feeding, either by word of mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h or writing, was by way of ſentence, ſo that no man might deny or doubt of any thing, which they deliuered. Neither was there any higher court, to which there might be any appeale from their ſentence, but all men were abſolutely bound to beleeue and obey whatſoeuer they taught and commanded. This wee grant, and herein we would agree with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> if this were all he meaneth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But he contenteth not himſelf with this kind of teaching; but will haue the teaching here ſpoken of, to be <hi>a difi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itiue ſentence declaring and determining what is reuealed, and what the ſenſe and meaning of it is,</hi> as I ſhewed chapter 4. numb. 7.</p>
            <p>To this muſt his proofes be applyed, which lie thus.</p>
            <p>If feeding <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15. be not teaching, by way of deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, what is reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led, and what the meaning of it is: Then we muſt vnderſtand it of preaching or writing commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> How ſhall the conſequence of this propoſition bee made good; ſince this feeding may (at the leaſt as reaſonably) be vnderſtood of reuealing the ſacred myſteries? yea this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is more reaſonable; becauſe the words were ſpoken to him, whoſe office it was to reueale thoſe myſteries by vertue of his Apoſtolicall commiſſion, as I ſhewed numb. 4. yea they are the very ſame in ſenſe and meaning, with thoſe that are vſed in the commiſſion, <hi>Goe teach all Nations, Mark.</hi> 16. 16. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 23. as was declared <hi>c. 4. n.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>But admit a man ſhould ſay, it is meant of preaching or writing: how doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> refute him? By telling vs that if we ſo take it, wee muſt condemne many Popes that haue written nothing at all.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> As if that were any inconuenience to vs; although to ſay the truth, moſt of the Popes that haue written, might haue had as much thanke to ſpare their labors, as to write as they haue done. Well, ſay we vnderſtand it of preaching. That may not be neither, ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Why ſo? becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21008:21"/> the Pope cannot preach to all: no, not diuers Popes to any at all: For as their owne Hiſtories confeſſe, ſome of them did not ſo much as vnderſtand their Grammar. But what if the Pope cannot? no more could any of the Apoſtles, nor <hi>Peter</hi> preach to all: yet had they authority to preach to all, as occaſion might happen; and were not reſtrained to this or that congregation, dioceſſe, prouince, nation, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and in that reſpect were vniuerſall Paſtors of the whole Church, yea euery one of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Aſſumption of</hi> Bellarmines <hi>ſyll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme. c. 3. n.</hi> 5.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> HItherto I haue ſhewed, what little ſhew of reaſon there is for that interpretation of <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtrength of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> concluſion principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth. I will now ſet my ſelfe to the ſifting of the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſecond part of his ſyllogiſme, which is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Peter and his ſucceſſors that feeding</hi> Iohn 21. 15. <hi>is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the propoſition, ſo the aſſumption alſo, containeth foure ſeuerall points, diſtinctly to be conſidered, that</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Thoſe words</hi> Iohn 21. <hi>are spoken to</hi> Peter.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>The office of ſeeding is committed to</hi> Peter.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Peter hath his ſucceſſours.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>The office of ſeeding is committed to</hi> Peters <hi>ſucceſſors.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The firſt of theſe foure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entences or points is rather ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed then expreſſed in the aſſumption; but it is plainly deliuered by <hi>Bellarmin. It is ſaid to</hi> Peter <hi>only, Feed my ſheepe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bel de Rom. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l c. 14. Sect. Hacten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Who denyeth this, if it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightly vnder?</p>
            <p>The ſpeech was directed immediately to <hi>Peter</hi> with whom our Lord then talked: but not ſo to <hi>Peter,</hi> as if the duty, to which he is exhorted, belonged to none but to <note place="margin">Inſtitut. lib. 4. cap. 6. n. 4.</note> him. Therefore <hi>Calvin</hi> truely ſaith, that <hi>as</hi> Peter <hi>receiued</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21008:22"/> 
               <hi>mandem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Iohn 21. 15. <hi>ſo all other miniſters are exhorted to feed the ſheepe,</hi> 1. Pet. 5. 2. and by ſo ſaying hee granteth, that thoſe words were ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> but hee telleth the Papiſts withall, that if they will proue, that they auouch, they muſt ſhew that <hi>whoſoeuer are commanded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o feed Chriſts ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eepe, to them the power ouer the whole Church is committed:</hi> In which words he denieth the conſequence of the propoſition, which he doth not expreſſe; but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the aſſumption contained in thoſe words, <hi>To</hi> Peter <note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. ponl. lib. 1. c. 14. Sect. Sed co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tra.</note> 
               <hi>onely Chriſt ſaid, feed my ſheepe.</hi> By which it is manifeſt, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth <hi>Caluin</hi> great wrong, in charging him with the denying, that thoſe words <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. are ſpoken to <hi>Peter</hi> onely: and ſpendeth his time and ſtrength in vaine to proue by ſeuen arguments againſt <hi>Caluin,</hi> that which <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> neuer denyed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But <hi>Bellarmines</hi> meaning is, that the words are ſo ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> that the thing ſignified by them belongeth not to the reſt of the Apoſtles. And in this ſenſe we ſay it is falſe, that <hi>thoſe words were spoken to</hi> Peter <hi>onely.</hi> If <hi>Bellarmine</hi> can not proue them true in this ſenſe (as I am ſure he cannot) his argument is nothing worth. For how ſhall that proue for <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors, againſt the reſt of the Apoſtles, which was ſpoken to them, as well as to him: yet it is not to be wondred at, that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> goeth not about to proue it in that ſenſe. For indeed there is no ſhew or colour of proofe for it, becauſe the Word of God no where maketh any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betwixt this <hi>feeding, Iohn</hi> 21. 15. and that <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Mat. 16. 16. Iohn</hi> 20. 21. which was enioyned <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles equally and alike, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. lib. 1. c. 12. Sect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ices.</note> confeſſeth. <hi>The keyes were giuen,</hi> Iohn 20. <hi>and 21. For when our Lord ſaid,</hi> (Iohn 20. 19.) <hi>Peace, be vnto you, as my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you, then hee gaue them the power or key of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. For by thoſe words hee made them as it were Legates and Gouernors of the Church, in his name. But in the words following, Receiue ye the holy Ghoſt: whoſe ſinnes yee remit, &amp;c. he gaue them the power of order:</hi> And thus much of the firſt propoſition of the foure.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21008:22"/>
            <p>The ſecond followeth, namely:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The office of feeding,</hi> Ioh. 21. <hi>is committed to</hi> Peter. This is affirmed in plaine words; and muſt bee vnderſtood of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> alone, not of him and the other Apoſtles. For that will not ſerue <hi>Bellarmines</hi> turne, becauſe it proues nothing for the Popes power, or againſt that wee defend. Beſides, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſtriues here for an office proper to <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe he cals it a ſingular office. But how can that be proper to <hi>Peter</hi> which is cominon to the reſt of the Apoſtles with him? This alſo we deny, as <hi>Caluin</hi> did long ſince; <hi>In this word</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Inſtitut. lib. 4. cap. 6. n. 4.</note> 
               <hi>feed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nothing is giuen to</hi> Peter, <hi>more then to the other. Bellarmine</hi> ſhould haue proued that this conueyeth a proper office to the Pope, and not haue taken that for granted, which he knoweth we alwayes deny. But hee doth not ſo much as offer to make any proofe of it, either <hi>de verbo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. cap. 5. Lib. 1. cap. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Dei,</hi> or <hi>de Roman. Pontif.</hi> in both which places he profeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſputeth the point. Indeed in the latter place, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that the words, <hi>Feed my ſheepe,</hi> were ſpoken to <hi>Peter</hi> only. But what is that to proue that <hi>feeding,</hi> Iohn 21. <hi>is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to</hi> Peter onely.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Some man perhaps will imagine, that the latter depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the former, but he wil quickly change his mind, if he doe but looke vpon them both together in one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thoſe words, feed my ſheepe, were spoken to</hi> Peter <hi>onely, then the feeding is commited to</hi> Peter <hi>onely;</hi> as if it were all one,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>To require or exhort</hi> Peter <hi>to feed, and</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To commit the feeding to</hi> Peter <hi>onely?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Put caſe a man that hath many ſeruants to goe about a peece of worke, reaping, or the like, ſhould ſay to ſome one of them whom he might ſuſpect of idleneſſe, <hi>Looke that you reape cleane and faire:</hi> Will any wiſe man conclude hereupon, that by theſe words hee giueth him an office to ouer-ſee and iudge of his other fellowes worke, or maketh him the onely worke-man? And yet it cannot be denyed that he ſpeaketh to him onely.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21008:23"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> But it will peraduenture bee replyed in defence of the conſequence of the forme propoſition, that if Chriſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Peter</hi> onely to feed, and did not commit that feeding onely to him, then there was no end or reaſon of his ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to him onely; but it were abſurd, yea blaſphemous, to ſay of our Sauiour, that there was no end or reaſon of his ſpeech. It were certainely blaſphemous for any man to ſay of the Lord Ieſus, that any action or ſpeech of his was without reaſon, or not to good purpoſe. But it were alſo a bold and blind preſumption, for any man to affirme, that there is no reaſon or end of our Sauiours ſpeech at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is none knowne to men. What if I know not the end or reaſon of it, may I conclude, that therefore there is none? So then if wee ſhould grant, that there can no reaſon bee giuen by vs, of our Sauiours ſpeech, vnleſſe thereby ſuch an office bee beſtowed vpon <hi>Peter;</hi> yet it might well bee, there was ſome reaſon thereof though vnknowne to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> But we can aſſigne good reaſon of that ſpeech: that is, we can ſhew, that there was good reaſon, why our Sauiour Chriſt ſhould direct his ſpeech in that ſort to <hi>Peter</hi> onely, though he meant not to place him in any office thereby. Firſt therefore wee ſay, that our Lord ſpeake to <hi>Peter</hi> thus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, that hee might giue him occaſion to make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his loue to him, which hee had brought into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, by denying his Maſter with ſwearing and curſing. And becauſe there was no meanes more effectuall to proue the continuance or renuing of <hi>Peter;</hi> loue to our Sauiour, then the feeding of his ſheepe, therefore our Sauiour preſſeth him with this duty aboue the reſt, becauſe there was more need to haue his loue ſhewed, then the others, who had not made their loue to him ſo doubtfull. Let me adde to theſe two a third, that it was needfull for <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe, that the execution of the commiſſion formerly giuen ſhould bee viged on <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe it might ſeeme, that by ſo ſoule a fall, hee had wholly beene put out of commiſſion: which doubt is fully remoued by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21008:23"/> charging him to goe forward in the execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. We ſhall not need then to make any ſuch conſtruction of the Lord Ieſus words, as if hee had intended by them to ſeale a commiſſion to <hi>Peter</hi> for an office to bee newly erected; for feare it ſhould be ſuſpected that thoſe words were to no purpoſe, or without reaſon. Nay rather moſt vnreaſonable is that conſequence, that would haue thoſe things inferre each other, betwixt which there is no kinde of agre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Peters <hi>ſucceſſours.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> NOw in the next place, the third propoſition offereth it ſelfe to be conſidered, although it bee but implyed, not expreſſed, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter hath his ſucceſſours,</hi> which is manifeſtly implyed, For he that ſaith, <hi>The office is committed to Peters ſucceſſors,</hi> ſuppoſeth that <hi>Peter hath ſucceſſors.</hi> This ſentence is thus to be vnderſtood; <hi>Peter onely hath his ſucceſſors, ſo as none of the other Apoſtles haue.</hi> For ſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> expoundeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. l. 1. c. 9. Sect. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeo, Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum.</note> 
               <hi>The chiefe eccleſiaſticall power was giuen to Peter, as to the ordinary paſtour, who was alwaies to haue ſucceſſors: to the other Apoſtles as to the delegates, who were not to haue ſucceſſors.</hi> And he ſaith, that <hi>The Biſhop of Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuccedeth</hi> Peter <hi>proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">L. 4. c. 25. Sect. Reſpondeo, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
               <hi>as the ordinary paſtour of the whole Church, but the Apoſtles were extraordinary, and as it were delegated paſtors, and ſuch haue no ſucceſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Peter</hi> hath ſucceſſors in the miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, wee confeſſe, and profeſſe: but wee adde, that this is common to him with the reſt of the Apoſtles. For the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explication whereof wee ſay, that to ſucceed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21008:24"/> is either to ſucceed them properly, as one King ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth another, or in ſimilitude or proportion, as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> truely ſaith. Wee grant that all the Apoſtles haue <note place="margin">De Rom Pon. l. c. 15. Sect. Dicun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur.</note> ſucceſſors in a proportion; namely, ſuch as preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, as they did, though not by reuelation; and that alſo haue power of ordination and iuriſdiction fit for the good gouernment of the Church. But we ſay none of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> haue any ſucceſſors of the ſecond kind. Therefore <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> might haue ſaued his labor in prouing that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. l 4 c. 25. Sect. ſta vero.</note> haue no ſuch ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Let vs ſee how he proueth that which we deny, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath ſucceſſors properly.</hi> This hee propoundeth in theſe tearmes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some muſt ſucceed</hi> Peter <hi>in the Biſhopricke of the whole</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. l. 2. c. 12. Sect. Primum ergo.</note> 
               <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which he doth more plainly declare, where he ſaith, that <hi>the Biſhop of Rome ſucceeds</hi> Peter <hi>properly, not as an Apoſtle,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">lib. 4 c. 25. Sect. Reſpond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
               <hi>but as an ordinary Paſtor ouer the whole Church.</hi> This we vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny, that <hi>Peter was to haue any ſuch ſucceſſor in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke of the whole Church.</hi> Our reaſon is, that <hi>Peter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had no ſuch office. But let vs ſee how <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would proue, that he had ſuch ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmines</hi> proofe of this point is ſet downe, and is thus <note place="margin">De Rom. Pont. l. 2. c. 12. Sect. Nos ergo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que.</note> to be framed.</p>
            <p>Either <hi>Peter</hi> hath ſucceſſors in Epiſcopall office ouer the whole Church, or that office periſhed at <hi>Peters</hi> death.</p>
            <p>But that office periſhed not at <hi>Peters</hi> death; for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was ordained for the good of the Church, and the Church hath had, and ſhall alwaies haue no leſſe need of it, then it had while <hi>Peter</hi> liued.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> hath ſucceſſors in the Epiſcopall office, ouer the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Who ſeeth not, that in this argument <hi>Bellar.</hi> taketh that for granted, which he ſhould proue, namely that <hi>Peter</hi> had ſuch <hi>an office while he liued?</hi> For he was not ignorant that all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants deny it? What is this elſe, according to <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Topicorum l. 8. cap. 13.</note> Philoſophy, but to beg the queſtion? <hi>He</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aristotle)</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21008:24"/> 
               <hi>that takes that as granted which he ought to proue, manifeſtly beggeth the queſtion.</hi> As for the proofes hee hath formerly brought, touching this office of <hi>Peter,</hi> I haue ſhewed, that they are weake and vaine, ſo that the point is ſtill as que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable as it was before. Therfore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is alſo guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a ſecond begging of the queſtion, becauſe his proofes are by-matters, as doubtfull, or more doubtfull then that is which he would proue by them. And of this manner of begging the queſtion, ſpeaketh the forenamed <hi>Ariſtole, Begging of the queſtion is, when the proofe is from things leſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prio. Analyt. l. 2. Cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>knowne, or equally</hi> vnknowne. <hi>And this is not</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) to demonſtrate the queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But what if we graunt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that which he cannot proue, that there was ſuch an office: yet may wee neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe deny his aſſumption, and ſay that;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Epiſcopall authority ouer the whole Church, periſhed at Peters death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will he tell vs that it was ordained for the good of the Church? What then? It will not follow thereupon that it muſt be perpetuall, vnleſſe he can ſhew, that our Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it ſhould continue for euer by ſucceſſion. For the whole courſe of publiſhing the Goſpell, and bringing men to true faith in Chriſt, dependeth wholly vpon the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, who being able to make any meanes effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall to his purpoſe, is not tyed to vſe any, but what pleaſe him. Therefore if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cannot ſhew that it was the ordinance of God, that ſuch an Epiſcopall function as he imagineth <hi>Peter</hi> had, ſhould be continued alwaies in the Church, it is no inconuenience to hold, that it periſhed with <hi>Peters</hi> death. And of this firſt argument enough.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> His ſecond Argument is in the ſaid twel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Chapter, <hi>Sect. ſecundo,</hi> and it is thus to be diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>If in the time of the Apoſtles there was one ſupreame Gouernour of the church, then there ought to be ſo now, becauſe the forme of the Church may not be changed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is one and the ſame at all times.</p>
            <p>But in the time of the Apoſtles there was one ſupreame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21008:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21008:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21008:26"/> Gouernour and head of the Church.</p>
            <p>Therefore there ought to be ſo now.</p>
            <p>The aſſumption, or ſecond part of this Syllogiſme, is as doubtfull as the concluſion inferred vpon it, and therefore it is a begging of the queſtion, not a proofe of the former Syllogiſme. But were it neuer ſo true, he were neuer the nearer; for the conſequence of the propoſition is naught, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no neceſſity, that the Church ſhould alwaies haue that office, which at any time it hath had. For, this neceſſity (if there were any ſuch) muſt ſpring out of the nature, either of God himſelfe, or of the Church, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon the decree of Gods will. To ſay there is any neceſſity in the nature of God, or of the Church, which may enforce the continuall being of that which once was, were abſurd. It remaineth then, that there muſt be ſome act of Gods will, by which it is decreed, that whatſoeuer office hath once been in the Church, ſhall be in it for euer, as I anſwered numb. 5. Wherefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> muſt ſhew vs ſome ordinance of God, for the continuance of ſuch go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment (ſuppoſing there was once ſuch an one) or giue vs leaue to reiect it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> He would make good the conſequence of the propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the proofe of it, againſt our exception, by this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <p>If the Church be one and the ſame at all times, then the forme of it may not be changed.</p>
            <p>But the Church is one and the ſame at all times.</p>
            <p>Therefore the forme of it may not be changed.</p>
            <p>In the antecedent part of the propoſition, and in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, by <hi>One, Bellarmine</hi> meaneth <hi>eſſentially one:</hi> by <hi>forme</hi> in the conſequent part, he vnderſtandeth, <hi>forme of gouernment.</hi> According to this ſenſe wee ſay, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the propoſition is naught: for the forme of the gouernment of the church, is not of the eſſence of the church, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> here vainly ſuppoſeth, and falſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes in his <note n="*" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſ lib. 3. cap 2 Sect. Noſtra autem.</note> definition of the church. The aſſumption rightly vnderſtood is true. The Church indeed is alwaies
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21008:26"/> one with Chriſt the head, becauſe of one and the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in him, and euery particular member of it. It is alſo one in faith, becauſe the true faith is one. But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that the church is one and the ſame, in reſpect of the gouernment and officers thereof. This we deny, and looke for better proofe of it from him, then his bare affirmation, in a matter of faith to bee beleeued vpon paine of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> There followeth a third proofe in the ſome twelfth chapter, <hi>Sect. tertio,</hi> after this ſort.</p>
            <p>If the Sheepe-fould endure to the end of the world, then ſucceſſors to <hi>Peter</hi> in that his chiefe paſtorall office muſt endure to the end of the world: For the office of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in the nature of the thing, muſt endure as long as the Sheepe-fould continueth, becauſe it is an ordinary and perpetuall office.</p>
            <p>But the Sheepe-fold endureth to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſucceſſours to <hi>Peter</hi> in that chiefe Paſtorall office muſt endure to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> kepeth his cuſtome to beg the queſtion. For here againe he taketh it for granted, that <hi>Peter</hi> was Paſtor of the whole church. But ſay it were ſo, what getteth he by it? For, the conſequence of his propoſition is naught, neither can the proofe hee bringeth make it good. The Sheepe-fold may endure to the end of the world, and yet that paſtorall Office not continue. Becauſe they doe not goe together in their nature; for if they did, then the one muſt be of the eſſence or being of the other, as a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule and man are: or ariſe out of the principles of the nature of the other, as ſpeech doth from the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble ſoule, which no man will ſay. Neither is there any ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God for the ioynt continuance of them together. <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ſeemeth to tell vs, that there is ſome ordinance of God for the <hi>knitting</hi> of them together. For he ſaith in proofe of his conſequence, that, <hi>That paſtorall Office is an ordinary &amp; perpetual office:</hi> as no office can be in the church, but by the diuine ordination. If he had ſhewed vs withall, where
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21008:27"/> we may finde that ordinance, he had ſaid ſomewhat to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Since neither he hath, nor we can finde any ſuch in the word of God, he muſt giue vs leaue to take it for no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of faith.</p>
            <p>Touching his aſſumption, I anſwer; that, <hi>If by Sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, he meane a company of people ſeparated from the world by the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion, and vnited together in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the diuine reuelation:</hi> Wee graunt that there is, and ſhall alwaies be ſuch a Sheepe-fold. But, if he dreame of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Sheepe-fold, he muſt proue his aſſumption, ore we can beleeue it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath not done, but ſetteth vpon vs with a freſh charge, in the ſame twelfth chapter, <hi>Sect, quinto:</hi> which is thus in due forme.</p>
            <p>Either ſome muſt ſucceed <hi>Peter</hi> in his Paſtorall office o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole church, or the church muſt bee without an head at <hi>Peters</hi> death and after.</p>
            <p>But the Church muſt not be without an head at <hi>Peters</hi> death, and after.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſome muſt ſucceed <hi>Peter</hi> in his paſtorall office.</p>
            <p>Here <hi>Bellarmine</hi> perceiued, that we were like enough to deny the propoſition, becauſe the diſiunction in it is naught, for that Chriſt the head of the church, continued to be the head thereof at <hi>Peters</hi> death, and ſhall do ſo for euer. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he telleth vs, it is not ſufficient for the Church to haue Chriſt for head; but that the Scripture maketh mention of another head of the Church, his reaſon lyeth thus:</p>
            <p>The head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. is not Chriſt, for that head <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 12.</note> hath need of the members, which is not true of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. is the head of the Church:</p>
            <p>Therefore there is ſome head of the Church which is not Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Wee eaſily yeeld the propoſition is true: and therfore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> needed not haue troubled himſelfe to proue it; eſpecially ſince his proofe is no better. For, our Sauiour, conſidered as the Mediatour, the head of the Church, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay to the Members, which make the body, I haue no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21008:27"/> neede of you, although, as he is God, he hath abſolutely no need of any of them.</p>
            <p>The aſſumption, that the head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12. is the head of the Church, we refuſe, as falſe. And how doth <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> proue it? As he doth many other points, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo. But this will not ſerue our turne in a matter of faith: Belike he looketh we ſhould diſproue it. Though it be no orderly courſe of diſputation, yet I ſay in a word, the <hi>head</hi> in that 21 verſe. in which the words quoted by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> ſignifies the naturall head, to which the principall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the church are reſembled; which, as principall as they are, cannot be without the feet, that is, the meaneſt members: And this interpretation is warranted by <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theophilact,</hi> who by head, vnderſtand, thoſe which had receiued greater gifts. So that indeed, the place containeth a compariſon, wherein the coniunction of the parts of the myſticall body, is declared by the like in the naturall body.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> There are two other arguments in the ſame chapter, <hi>Sect. Sexto,</hi> and <hi>Sect. Denique:</hi> the one is drawne from the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the high Prieſts in the old Teſtament: the other from the neceſſity of monarchicall gouernment in the church. But they are ſo ſleight and idle, that I ſhould but waſt time, labour, and paper to meddle with them: where-I thus end this third point and this Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21008:28"/>
            <head>CHAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Feeding committed to</hi> Peters <hi>Succeſſours.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe fourth and laſt point to be conſidered in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Chapt. 5 num. 5. &amp; chap. 8. num.</note> aſſumption, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feeding,</hi> Ioh. 21. <hi>is committed to Peters Succeſſors alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This we ſay is vntrue; and will make it appeare to bee <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 21. 25.</note> ſo, by anſwering the arguments he bringeth to proue it. <note place="margin">Bellarm. leverbo De, il. b. 3 cap 5. Sect. Quartum.</note> The firſt whereof is in this manner:</p>
            <p>Either our Sauiour, when he required <hi>Peter</hi> to feed his ſheepe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. ſpake alſo to his ſucceſſors: or elſe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for his church for twenty fiue yeares onely, and not to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>But when he required <hi>Peter</hi> to feed his ſheepe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. he prouided for his Church, not for fiue and twenty years onely, but to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. he ſpake alſo to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Concerning the aſſumption, we ſay, that wee are out of doubt, our Sauiour by thoſe words prouided for his church to the end of the world. For hee thereby required <hi>Peter</hi> to publiſh the Goſpell by reuealing it. Now this reuealing or preaching of the Goſpell by reuelation, is and ſhall be of great vſe to the Church, in all ages and times, ſo long as the world ſhall endu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. And in this ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I grant the aſſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but in <hi>Bellermines</hi> ſenſe, that our Sauiour prouided for his Church by inſtituting ſuch an Office as hee fancieth, which the whole argument preſumeth, I deny the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and propoſition too.</p>
            <p>Indeed, the propoſition is vtterly falſe: our Lord proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the Church to the end of the world, though hee ſpake not at all in that place to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors. For in thoſe words hee tooke order for the reuealing of the Goſpell, which reuelation of <hi>Peters,</hi> containeth prouiſion for the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21008:28"/> Church to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There is a ſecond argument of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> to the ſame <note place="margin">Bellarm. do Pont. Rom. l. 2, cap. 12. Sect. quinto.</note> purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In which words Chriſt committed all his ſheepe, both for place and time to <hi>Peter;</hi> in thoſe he ſpoke to <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors alſo: for <hi>Peter</hi> was not to liue alwaies in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>But in thoſe words, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21. Chriſt committed all his ſheepe, both for place and time to <hi>Peter.</hi> For, it behoued our Sauiour to haue no leſſe care of vs, then of our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
            <p>Therefore in thoſe words, <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. Chriſt ſpake to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors alſo.</p>
            <p>Of the aſſumption, which ſpeaketh of our Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting his ſheepe to <hi>Peter,</hi> by thoſe words, there hath beene enough ſaid already in the former chapter, which needeth no repetition.</p>
            <p>The propoſition I reiect as falſe. For our Sauiour might well by thoſe words commit all his ſheepe, for place and time, to <hi>Peters</hi> Feeding, by the doctrine of the Goſpell to be reuealed, which was to continue, as by Gods bleſſing it hath done, and ſhall doe; no leſſe to vs and our poſterity, then to our predeceſſors, from time to time, whereby hee ſheweth his care of vs, as well as of them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Now for a concluſion of this fourth point, and a full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to this whole argument, drawn from thoſe words <hi>Iohn</hi> 21. 15. I will propound a reaſon or two out of the text it ſelfe, by which it ſhall appeare, if not neceſſarily, yet with as great likelihood as any thing <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath brought in this queſtion, that our Lord ſpake to <hi>Peter</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to his ſucceſſors alſo.</p>
            <p>Of them to whom thoſe words were ſpoken, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our demanded whether they loued him, or no.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Peter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſucceſſors, Chriſt did not demand whether they loued him or no: for they neither were there in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nor at all in being in the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours thoſe words were not ſpoken.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21008:29"/>
            <p>He to whom thoſe words were ſpoken, had giuen occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that our Sauiour ſhould repeat this queſtion thrice. For it is not likely that our Lord would haue repeated them ſo often, if there had not beene occaſion giuen: and wee finde iuſt occaſion of repeating them thrice, in <hi>Peters</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him thrice.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors had giuen no occaſion of the three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold repetition: for, they neither were at that time, nor had beene before in the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore to <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors thoſe words were not ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thus haue I at the laſt examined this argument of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines,</hi> with all the proofes of euery ſeuerall part thereof, whereby it hath appeared (I doubt not) to euery iudicious and vnpartiall Reader, that there is no force in it to proue, that the Church or Pope hath a commiſſion from our Lord Ieſus, to teach the whole Church by way of iudging and determining, what is to be beleeued of all men, and what is not. It will bee looked for perhaps, that I ſhould proceed to the diſcuſsing of ſome other, that are brought for the proofe of this queſtion. But I thinke it would bee but loſt labour: for <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who was as able as any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh writer, that hath dealt with this matter, and had allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that he wirt (eſpecially in a point that ſo nearely touched the Popes free-hold) if not from the Conſiſtory immediately, yet with the knowledge thereof, from the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice appointed for that purpoſe in Rome, ſetteth vp his reſt vpon that place in <hi>Iohn</hi> and telleth vs confidently; that, <hi>Then onely Peter receiued the keyes of the kingdome, as princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de Rom. Pont. lib. 1. c. 12. Sect. vt autem.</note> 
               <hi>and ordinary gouernour, when he heard thoſe words, Feede my ſheepe: and then alſo</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>the charge of the reſt of the Apoſtles, his brethren, was committed to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Therefore ſince we require a commiſsion for ſuch an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that is either here or no where to bee found: to what purpoſe ſhould we examine other arguments, which can proue no ſuch matter? Now that we haue good reaſon to call for the ſight of a commiſsion, by which, ſuch an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21008:29"/> office ſhould be erected, no reaſonable man can doubt, if he conſider, what himſelfe would doe, if any man ſhould chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to himſelfe the authority of the Lord Chancellor, or Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England:</hi> would he take his word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge of his commiſſion vnder the broad ſeale? And why then ſhould wee be ſo ſimple, as in a buſineſſe of ſuch importance, to take the word of a Cardinall, for the Popes prerogatiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Ieſuit, after ſome other Papiſts, allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth for the proofe of this commiſſion, <hi>Mat. 28. 19. Goe teach all Nations.</hi> But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath diſclaimed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued all commiſſion in that place: and that not without reaſon. For (he ſaith) <hi>Then onely he receiued the keyes of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pont. l. 1. c. 12. Sect. Vt autem.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdome, as principall and ordinarie gouernour, when he heard, Feed my ſheepe.</hi> In this he diſclaimeth it, his diſproofe is, that <hi>the commiſſion,</hi> Mat. 28. 19. <hi>is all one with that</hi> Ioh. 20. 21. <hi>as that which</hi> by <hi>Bellarmines</hi> confeſſion Sect. <hi>Dices. containeth power both of order and iuriſdiction:</hi> which is alſo conueyed to the Apoſtles, <hi>Math. 28. 20. Goe teach and baptize.</hi> And this Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> muſt needs acknowledge, if he will haue that place be a commiſſion for the Popes authority. As for that <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 21. the power there was not committed ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but to all the Apoſtles, as to Legates, not to ordinary paſtors; as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> noteth. All other <note place="margin">Sect. Vt autem.</note> places of Scripture brought by the Papiſts to this purpoſe, are of the ſame kind, and concerne all the Apoſtles as well as <hi>Peter:</hi> wherefore all this conſidered, I hold it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needleſſe, to meddle with thoſe other eight arguments of <hi>Bellarmines,</hi> which indeed are of another kinde; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe, that I haue ſaid enough of that weake foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Papiſts faith, the authority of the Church in perſon of the Pope for the time being. Whereupon I infer my former concluſion, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſaith of the Church of Rome is erroneous and falſe, euen in the very foundation of it; and therefore to bee refuſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected of all men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21008:30"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Containing a ſecond proofe, that the faith of the Church of Rome is erroneous and falſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> SVch as the foundation of the Romiſh faith is, ſuch is the faith it ſelfe; namely, falſe and erroneous, as I will ſhew by the argument that followes, in the ſeuerall parts of it.</p>
            <p>If ſome of the Articles of the faith of the Church of Rome bee falſe and erroneous, then the faith of that Church is falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>But ſome of the Articles of the faith of the Church of Rome are falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>Therefore the faith of the Church of Rome is falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Leſt any man ſhould haſtily except againſt the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the propoſition, as if I went about to proue the whole by the part, which may not bee; I muſt intreat him to remember, that (as I noted before) in this queſtion, wee take the faith of the Church of Rome, for one intire thing, becauſe of that one bond, the authority of the Church or Pope, by which all the parts of it are ſo ioyned together, that they all make but one body. By reaſon of which bond he that refuſeth any one part reiecteth the whole. For by that his refuſall, he accuſeth their Church of errour, and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in determining matters of faith, and ſo ouerthroweth the very foundation of their faith. Beſides, the denying of any one ſuch Article, let it bee in it ſelfe of neuer ſo ſmall importance, draweth vpon the denyer that <hi>Anathema</hi> or curſe, which ſeizeth on all them which are not of the faith of the Church of Rome. Wherefore I may preſume with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſumption, that the conſequence is good, ſeeing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Article is equally and alike a matter of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> My aſſumption, I will make good by ſetting downe out of the Councill of <hi>Trent</hi> diuers Articles of the Romiſh ſaith, which are falſe and erroneous: and theſe they are,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21008:30"/>1 <hi>The ſauing verity</hi> [or truth] <hi>taught by Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, is contained in written bookes,</hi> [or Scriptures] <hi>and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written traditions.</hi> Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 4. decret. de Canon. Scripturae.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The bookes of</hi> Iudith, Tobit, Eſter <hi>[chap.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. Wiſdome, Eccleſiaſticus, Baruch, Daniel] <hi>chap.</hi> 3. 13, 14. Macchabees 1, 2. <hi>are canonicall ſcripture.</hi> d. decret. de ſcriptur.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>The whole bookes of Scripture, and euery part of them, as they are in the vulgar Latine edition, are to be receiued for ſacred and canonicall.</hi> d. decret. de ſcriptur.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>It is the office of the Church to iudge of the true ſenſe,</hi> [or interpretation] <hi>of the ſacred</hi> [or holy] <hi>Scriptures.</hi> d. ſeſſ. 4. de edit. &amp; vſu librorum ſacrorum, Sect. inſuper.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>The Biſhop of Rome is Gods Vicar on earth.</hi> Seſſ. 6. decret. de reform. cap. 1. and ſeſſ. 14. de poenitentia, cap. 7.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>The Church of Rome is the mother and Miſtris of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> Seſſ. 7. de baptiſ. can. 3. and ſeſſ. 13. de extrem. vnct. cap. 3. and ſeſſ. 22. de ſacrif. miſſae. cap. 8.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>Grace</hi> [beſtowed in baptiſme] <hi>doth take away whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath the true &amp; proper nature of ſin.</hi> ſeſſ. de pec. orig. can. 5.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Concupiſcence in the regenerate is not truely and properly ſinne.</hi> d. canon. 5.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Man doth freely aſſent to, and cooperate</hi> [or worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther] <hi>with Gods exciting and cooperating grace, ſo that he can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo reiect</hi> [or refuſe] <hi>the ſame grace.</hi> Seſſ. 6. de iuſtif. cap. 5. <hi>And deſſent if he will.</hi> can. 4.</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>The onely formall cauſe of iuſtification, is iuſtice</hi> [or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe] <hi>inhaerent.</hi> d. ſeſſ. de iuſtit. cap. 7.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>By keeping the commandements of the Church, a man doth encreaſe in the iuſtice, which he receiued by the grace of Chriſt, and is more iuſtified.</hi> cap. 10.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>The iuſt in ſome actions doe not ſin venially.</hi> cap. 11.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>By euery mortall ſinne a man falleth away from the grace of iustification, which he had receiued.</hi> cap. 14, 15. and can. 23.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>By the Sacrament of poenance the grace of iuſtification, which was loſt, is recouered.</hi> cap. 14.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21008:31"/>15 <hi>The good workes of a man that is iuſtified, are his merits.</hi> can. 32.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>The iuſt truely deſerue euerlaſting life by works wrought in God.</hi> cap. 16. and can. 32.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>vnleſſe a man faithfully and firmely beleeue the Catholick doctrine of the Council of Trent touching iustification, he cannot be ſaued.</hi> cap. 16. Sect. Poſt hanc.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Some that are not predeſtinate receiue the grace of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> can. 17.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>The Sacraments of the new Teſtament are neither more nor fewer then 7, to wit, 1 Baptiſme, 2 Confirmation, 3 The Lords Supper, 4 Poenance, 5 Extreame Vnction, 6 Ordination, 7 Matrimony: and euery one of theſe is truely and properly a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi> ſeſſ. 7. de ſacram: in genere, can. 1.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Baptiſme, Confirmation, and Ordination imprint in the ſoule a character that cannot be blotted out.</hi> can. 9.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>The ſacraments of the new Teſtament, containe the thing they ſignifie, and beſtow it vpon them, that hinder it not.</hi> can. 6. <hi>And vpon all as much as is required on Gods part.</hi> can. 7. <hi>And that by the worke wrought.</hi> can. 8.</p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>After the conſecration of the bread and wine in the Lords Supper, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt true God and man is contained, truely, really and ſubſtantially vnder the ſhewes of thoſe ſenſible things,</hi> ſeſſ. 13. de ſacram. Euchariſt. cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>The holy Euchariſt is to be reſerued in the Chancell, and caried honorably to the ſicke.</hi> cap. 6.</p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>The tenth Commandement, Thou ſhalt not couet, is rent in ſunder and made two by the Council of Trent.</hi> ſeſſ. 14. de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, cap. 5. and can. 7.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>The time of Lent is holy and moſt acceptable.</hi> ſeſſ. 14. de poenitentia, cap. 5.</p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>No man that knowes himſelfe to be guilty of mortall ſinne, how contrite ſoeuer he ſeeme to himſelfe to be, may come to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euchariſt, without ſacrament all confeſſion going before.</hi> d. ſeſſ. 13. cap. 7. and can. 11. that is, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill hee haue confeſſed all and euery one of his mortall ſinnes, and alſo thoſe circumſtances, which change the kind of the ſinne,</hi> ſeſſ. 14. de ſacram. poenitentia, c. 5.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21008:31"/> 
               <hi>And that to a Prieſt in ſecret.</hi> can. 6. 7.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Power</hi> [or authority] <hi>was giuen to the Apoſtles and their lawfull ſucceſſors to remit and retaine ſinnes for the reconciling of ſuch of the faithfull as fall after Baptiſme.</hi> ſeſſ. 14. de ſacram ent. poenitentiae, cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="28">28 <hi>It is vtterly falſe and differing from the word of God to ſay, that the Lord God neuer remitteth the fault, but with all he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth the whole puniſhment.</hi> d. ſeſſ. 14. de poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it. cap. 8. &amp; can. 12. &amp; ſeſſ. 6. de iuſtif. cap. 14. can. 30.</p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Neither the Lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, nor any Clergy man that doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate, is bound by any Commandement of God, to receiue vnder both kinds.</hi> ſeſſ. 21. de ſacram. ſub utraque ſpecie, cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>The Church hath decreed it for law, that all the Laity, and the Clergy, that doe not conſecrate ſhould receiue vnder one kind onely.</hi> d. ſeſſ. cap. 5.</p>
            <p n="31">31 <hi>We may make ſatisfaction to God through Ieſus Chriſt by temporall afflictions layed on vs by God, and borne patiently by vs.</hi> ſeſſ. 14 de ſacram. poenitent. cap. 9. &amp; can. 13.</p>
            <p n="32">32 <hi>The Prieſthood was not to bee aboliſhed by the death of Chriſt,</hi> ſeſſ. 22. de ſacrif. miſſae. cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Our Sauiour Chriſt by theſe words, This doe in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me, charged his Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours to offer his body and blood vnder the ſignes of bread and wine,</hi> d. cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="34">34 <hi>Water is to be mingled with wine in the Chalice that is to be offered,</hi> d. ſeſſ. cap. 7.</p>
            <p n="35">35 <hi>The names of Subdeacons, Acolytes, Exorciſts, Lectors and Doore-keepers, and the proper office of euery one of theſe, hath beene euer ſince the beginning of the Church.</hi> ſeſſ. 23. de ſacram. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinis, cap. 2. and de reformat. cap. 28.</p>
            <p n="36">36 <hi>Matrimony contracted, not conſummated is diſſolued by the ſolemne profeſſion of religion by either party.</hi> ſeſſ. 24. de ſacram. Matrimon. can. 6.</p>
            <p n="37">37 <hi>There is a Purgatory,</hi> ſeſſ. 25. decret. de purgat.</p>
            <p n="38">38 <hi>The ſoules which raigne with Chriſt do offer vp their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God for men.</hi> ſeſſ. 25. decret. de innocatione ſanctorum.</p>
            <p n="39">39 <hi>It is good &amp; profitable humbly to call vpon the ſaints fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, and to fly to their prayer, helpe, and furtherance, for the obtaining of benefits,</hi> [or bleſſings] <hi>from God by his ſonne Ieſus</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21008:32"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt our Lord.</hi> d. decret. de inuocat.</p>
            <p n="40">40 <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eneration and honor are due to the reliques of the Saints</hi> Seſſ. 25. decret. de inuocat. venerat. &amp; reliq. ſanctorum.</p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>The Images of Saints, and other ſacred monuments are not honored without profit, &amp;c. The memories</hi> [or monuments] <hi>of the Saints are not frequented in vaine for the obtaining of their helpe.</hi> d decret. de venerat.</p>
            <p n="42">42 <hi>The Images of Chriſt, and the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and other Saints are to be had and retained eſpecially in Churches, and due honor and veneration is to be giuen them,</hi> d. ſeſſ. 25. de ſacris I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginum.</p>
            <p n="43">43 <hi>The power of granting indulgences was committed by Chriſt to the Church, and the vſe of them is helpfull to Chriſtian people.</hi> d. ſeſſ. 25. decret. de indulgent.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That many Articles of the faith of the Church of Rome are falſe and erroneous.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> VPon the 43 propoſitions ſet downe out of the Councill of Trent in the former chapter, I thus argue to proue the faith of the Church of Rome erroneous.</p>
            <p>The aforeſaid Articles or propoſitions are falſe and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</p>
            <p>The aforeſaid Articles or propoſitions are articles of the faith of the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſome of the Articles or propoſitions of the faith of the Church of Rome are falſe and erroneous.</p>
            <p>Touching theſe propoſitions, that they are articles of the ſaith of the Church of Rome, it is euident, becauſe we finde them in the Council of Trent, propounded to be beleeued of all Chriſtians. Are theſe all, will ſome man ſay, wherein we diſſent from them, and which we reiect as erroneous? No, there are many other and ſome of them of no ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I hold theſe onely needfull to be debated: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21008:32"/> the other ſo depend vpon theſe, that if theſe bee falſe, none of them can be true. For example, It is ſaid article 36. that <hi>there is a purgatory,</hi> if this cannot be proued, then it is falſe, that <hi>the Saints in Purgatery are holpen by the ſuffrages of the faithfull, or ſacrifice of the altar:</hi> which yet is deliuered as an article of faith in that decree. Againe, it is affirmed ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle 32. that <hi>Chriſt appointed his Apostles and their ſucceſſors to offer his body and blood vnder the ſignes of bread and wine.</hi> If there bee no ſuch commandement of our Sauiours, then 1 <hi>There is no Maſſe. 2 The vertue of the bloody ſacrifice is not applyed by the ſacrifice of the Maſſe. 3 The ſacrifice of the Maſſe is not truely propitiatory.</hi> All which are propounded for Articles of ſaith by the forenamed Councill, ſeſſ. 22. de ſacrificio Meſſae. I might ſay the like of many other points, but theſe may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It remaineth that I proue the propoſition, which muſt be done by handling the points ſeuerally: Firſt therefore I thus begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſauing truth</hi> [or verity] <hi>taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſſ 4. decret. de Can. Script.</note> 
               <hi>is contained</hi> (ſaith the Councill) <hi>in written bookes</hi> [or in the Scriptures] <hi>or in vnwritten traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this propoſition or Article wee muſt vnderſtand, that the Scriptures and traditions are made diuers parts of that record, wherein the ſauing truth is contained: ſo that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe parts containeth all, but the one ſome, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome, which appeareth plainly by the Council it ſelfe, where, deſcribing Traditions, it ſaith, that <hi>They are not wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> that <hi>They were receiued by word of mouth from the Apoſtles and were deliuered to them either by our Sauiour, or by his spirit, and haue beene ſo conueyed from hand to hand to the preſent Church.</hi> And indeed if this were not the Councils mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, they ſaid nothing at all againſt vs: who make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but that the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which liued preſently after the Apoſtles, did truely gather diuers points out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which haue worthily beene receiued and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from time to time. Such for inſtances, were theſe points; that <hi>our Lord Ieſus is true God,</hi> that <hi>the holy Ghoſt is</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21008:33"/> 
               <hi>true God,</hi> that <hi>our Sauiour Chriſt conſiſteth of two diſtinct na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> that <hi>He is but one perſon, not two.</hi> Theſe points the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians rightly drew out of the Scriptures. For they bee not expreſſed there in ſo many words: and theſe were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to bee Articles of faith by the foure firſt generall Councils againſt <hi>Arius, Macedonius, Eutiches,</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius.</hi> Of this kind there are many traditions in the Church, and will daily be more, as it ſhall pleaſe God to bleſſe the labors of his ſeruants in the reading &amp; vnderſtanding of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Of theſe we diſpute not, but onely of ſuch, as are not compriſed in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It would alſo bee obſerued, that the Councill ſaith not barely and ſimply <hi>truth,</hi> but <hi>ſauing truth:</hi> which, in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, was put into the decree, becauſe we grant that ſome things concerning rites and ceremonies, were deliuered by <note place="margin">Bellar de verbo Dei non ſcripto l. 4 c 3. Sect Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo diſſidemus</note> our Lord or his Apoſtles, which are not recorded in the Scriptures, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, whereas the Councill ſaith, <hi>the ſauing truth, taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> wee muſt inquire whether they meane vniuerſally and wholly whatſoeuer our Sauiour and his Apoſtles taught, not any one ſentence excepted; or onely ſo much, as was intended for the perpetuall vſe of the Church: That it meaneth abſolutely <hi>all ſauing truth ſo taught,</hi> it may be probably gathered out of the very words of the Councill. For it ſaith, that <hi>The preaching of Chriſt and his Apoſtles is the fountaine of all ſauing truth;</hi> and by and by addeth, <hi>which truth is contained in written bookes and vnwritten traditions:</hi> which is all one, as if the Councill ſhould haue ſaid in plaine termes, <hi>All ſauing truth taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles is contained in written books and vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thus haue we the meaning of the Councill, now that it may appeare what is true in it, what falſe, I will draw it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeuerall propoſitions, namely theſe 3.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>All ſauing truth taught by Chriſt and his Apostles, is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for future ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Some ſauing truth is contained in written bookes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21008:33"/> 3 <hi>Some ſauing truth is comprehended in vnwritten traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two latter propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſecond and third, are manifeſtly in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at article of the Councell: the firſt of the three is neceſſarily implyed: For if ſome things taught by them remaine not to poſterity, then all ſauing truth ſo taught, is not to be found in the Scripture and tradition, becauſe ſome of it is not at all recorded. In the ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: that, <hi>Some truth taught by Christ and his Apoſtles is contained in the Scripture:</hi> wee wholly agree with them, and ſay farther in particular: that, <hi>All ſuch truths are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd therein, as the Lord appointed for the ſaluation of the Elect in all ages.</hi> And this is the meaning of our Diuines, when they ſay; that, <hi>All things neceſſary to ſaluation are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Scriptures.</hi> Which is manifeſt by D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Reynolds:</hi> for, <note place="margin">D. <hi>Reynolds</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his ſixe concluſions, at concluſion firſt. D <hi>Whitaker de ſcript. q. 6. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> ſaying; that, <hi>The Lord teacheth the Church all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſaluation,</hi> he expoundeth <hi>neceſſary to ſaluation,</hi> thus; <hi>which lead the faithfull to ſaluation and life.</hi> And D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> propounding our opinion of the ſame matter, in the ſame manner, interpreteth, <hi>neceſſary to ſaluation,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>by the way of life:</hi> ſignifying thereby; that, <hi>Thoſe things are neceſſary to ſaluation, which teach vs the way to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> Reuerend B. <hi>Iewell</hi> ſpeakes to the ſame purpoſe; <note place="margin">B. <hi>Iewells Apol. part.. 2. c. 9. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſ. 1.</hi>
               </note> that, <hi>The Scriptures doe fully comprehend all things whatſoeuer bee needfull for our health: and that they be the very might and ſtrength of God to attaine to ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Whereby it is manifeſt, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dealt falſly and <note place="margin">De verbo Dei non ſcripte l. 4. l. 3. Sect. Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſia.</note> deceitfully when he propounded the queſtion. <hi>The contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>betwixt vs and the Heretickes, is, that we ſay, The whole doctrine neceſſary to faith and manners is not contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scriptures expreſly; and therefore beſides the written word of God, there is alſo an vnwritten word of God required; that is to ſay: Diuine and Apoſtolicall traditions.</hi> Wherefore I will leaue <hi>Bellarmine</hi> with his frauds, and debate the point as it is deliuered in the Councell of Trent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> For the firſt: that, <hi>All ſauing truth, taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is recorded for future ages, Bellarmine</hi> bringeth no proofe: and yet he could not chooſe but ſee, that there is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21008:34"/> no neceſſity in the point it ſelfe, why we ſhould take it for true. For it might well be, that our Sauiour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught ſome things, which tended to the ſaluation of ſome particular men, not of all men, and therfore might be left vnrecorded without any loſſe, or damage, to the Church. Therefore we may iuſtly call for proofe of a point ſo vncertaine, that is made by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> a matter of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The third propoſition at numb. 5. is; that, <hi>Some ſauing truth is comprehended in tradition.</hi> For the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and cleering whereof, wee are firſt to learne, what vnwritten traditions are. Which the Councell of Trent teacheth vs. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten traditions, are things endicted by our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 4. decret. de canon ſcript.</note> 
               <hi>Sauiour, by word of mouth, or by the holy Ghoſt, and kept in the Church by continuall ſucceſſion.</hi> We may content our ſelues with this deſcription, without ſeeking any explication out of <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> or any other, becauſe <hi>Bellarmines</hi> definition, that, <hi>A tradition is a doctrine, not written by the firſt author thereof,</hi> is ſo far from making the meaning of the Councell of Trent plaine, that indeed, it doth rather more obſcure <note place="margin">Bellarm. de verb. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l 4. c. 2. Sect. Vocatur.</note> it. The Councell ſetteth downe no diſtribution of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions but this; that, <hi>ſome of them concerne faith ſome manners.</hi> But <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> wearieth himſelfe and his Reader, with a number of diſtrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ions, which, as I ſaid of his deſcription, are of no vſe, but to darken the queſtion. Tradition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus vnderſtood, I ſay, that third propoſition is falſe, and the contradictory thereof, true. <hi>No ſauing truth, taught by Chriſt or his Apoſtles is contained in vnwritten traditions:</hi> which may thus appeare: If no part of the Scripture refer vs to tradition, for ſome part of Gods word, not contained in the ſaid Scriptures, then haue we no reaſon to ſeeke for any part thereof in tradition. For the Scriptures doe ſend vs to the ſcriptures for the knowledge of ſauing truth, <hi>Ioh. 5. 39. Search the Scriptures, for in them ye thinke to haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 15. ſaith: that, <hi>The</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture is able to make vs wiſe to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And wold not the ſcripture, trow we, haue ſent vs to tradition for ſupply of that which was wanting in it, if there had beene any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21008:34"/> to be had therein? For, it was as eaſie and as orderly for the Scripture to referre vs to tradition, as to it ſelfe: and as well beſeeming the wiſdome and prouidence of God, to haue ſent vs to both parts of his word by the Scriptures, as to the one of them: yea, it was a great deale more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, For no man could doubt, but he was to haue recourſe to the Scriptures, becauſe they were knowne to be the word of God. But who could haue imagined that the Lord God, teaching vs ſo plentifully in the Scriptures, would leaue out ſome part of the ſauing truth, and not ſo much as giue vs any inkling thereof, nor direct vs where we might finde it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> But they tell vs, the Scripture doth put vs ouer for ſome of the diuine truth, to vnwritten traditions. Let vs ſee and examine the places that are brought to this purpoſe by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de verb. Dei non ſcripto l. 4. c. 5. Sect. Ac primum.</note> who made choiſe of the beſt places, that had beene, or could be alledged in this matter. The firſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is thus to be concluded.</p>
            <p>Thoſe things which our Sauiour ſpake of, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. 12. and <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 12. and 21. 25.</note> 21. 25. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 3. are comprehended in tradition. For they are not written: and it is not credible, that the Apoſtles which heard them did not deliuer them to the Church. Surely they were neither ſo enuious that they would not, nor ſo forgetfull that they could not.</p>
            <p>But thoſe things which he ſpake in thoſe places, were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing truths.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſome ſauing truths, taught by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, are contained in tradition.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Ere I anſwer to this argument particularly, I muſt note in general, that euery propoſition of euery argument brought in this queſtion muſt be certainly and euidently true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the point concluded is an article of faith, which muſt be either expreſly ſet downe by the holy Ghoſt, or colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the word of God, by manifeſt and neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. Therefore if we finde any propoſition in any ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that is not in ſuch ſort true, the concluſion cannot be an Article of faith, becauſe of thoſe premiſes: but is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21008:35"/> at the moſt probable, as they are.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Particularly I ſay of this argument, that no Article of faith can bee concluded by it, becauſe the propoſition or Maior, with the proofe of it, are at the moſt but probable, as the examining of the reaſon will ſhew.</p>
            <p>Either our Sauiors ſpeeches the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e mentioned are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in tradition, or elſe they remaine not at all to poſterity.</p>
            <p>But they remaine to poſterity: for the Apoſtles did not omit the recording of them, ſince they were neither enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nor forgetfull.</p>
            <p>Therefore our Sauiours ſpeeches there mentioned are contained in tradition.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Firſt, this argument preſumeth that whatſoeuer our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſpake, was ſome way or other committed to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And this was the firſt propoſition in this doctrine of the Council, &amp; denied by vs, n. 5. &amp; 7. therfore <hi>Bellar.</hi> doth but play the ſophiſter by begging the queſtion, &amp; proueth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Secondly, I anſwer, that if I ſhould grant him that he beggeth, yet his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opoſition would be falſe. For the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction is nought. What if I ſay, thoſe ſpeeches of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour neither periſhed, nor remaine in tradition, but are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in ſome part of the Apoſtles writings in the new Teſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For ſince our Sauior promiſed <hi>Ioh. 16. 13. to ſend them his spirit which ſhould lead them into all truth,</hi> and <hi>Ioh. 14. 26 bring to their remembrance all things, which he had told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> and performed what he promiſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 3. It is more then likely, that they did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the things to poſterity, which he cauſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to remember: for why elſe were they brought to their remembrance? But wee find no other courſe, that eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r they tooke to deliuer the Goſpell to poſterity, but writing. Why then ſhould theſe points be kept vnwritten? Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely they are neither greater myſteries, nor ſmaller mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, then ſome that are written.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The propoſition then is either falſe or doubtfull, and the aſſumption little better. For how can <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe matters be recorded in any of the Apoſtles wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings or no, vnleſſe he know what they were, as he will not for very ſhame ſay he doth.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21008:35"/>
            <p>But If we doubt of it, he would make vs beleeue wee accuſe the Apoſtles of envie or negligence. God forbid. We will grant him any thing almoſt, rather then lay ſuch an imputation upon thoſe glorious inſtruments of our ſalvation. We haue a better way to anſwer then ſo, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> commeth ſhort of his reckonig, <hi>either of negligence or enuy.</hi> What needeth that? It may well be, that they did not record every one of our Saviour ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, becauſe they had no commiſſion to leaue them on record: and they were to doe according to their comiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; being to deliver the word of God, as they were inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the holy Ghoſt, not to ſet downe every thing they could remember, as men doe that follow their owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſcretion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Neither can <hi>Bellarmine</hi> any way make good the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the principall Syllogiſme negatiue, that Thoſe things, which our Lord ſpake of in thoſe places, were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truths, except he can certainely tell, what they were.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Bellarmines <hi>ſecond and third Arguments to proue vnwritten traditions.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>BEllarmines</hi> ſecond argument in the place aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, muſt be thus ordered. <note place="margin">a Bellar. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei non ſcript. lib. 4. cap. 5. ſect. Secundum teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ordinances which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of,</hi> 1. Cor. 11. 2, <hi>are not written; for they concerne the manner of praying and receiuing the Sacraments: and theſe we find not written any where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ordinances which the Apoſtle there ſpeaketh of, are ſauing truths; for he commendeth the Corinthians for keeping them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truths are contained in vnwritten tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21008:36"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The propoſition taketh it for granted, that whatſoeuer the Apoſtles taught, is committed to poſteritie. But this we denie: as I ſhewed cap. 12. n. 7. How then ſhall this argument proue, that the concluſion is an article of faith?</p>
            <p>Well, admit it were true: yet is, the propoſition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, as the proofe ſheweth; For out of doubt, it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſt of it ſelfe. The proofe lieth thus.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer was deliuered to the Apoſtles, and is not found written any where, that is kept in vnwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ordinances the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, were deliuered by him, and are not found written any where.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therefore the ordinances the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, are kept in vnwritten tradition.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The propoſition of this Syllogiſme is vntrue. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not found, yet it may be written: diuers things are contained in the Scriptures, which are not knowne to be there contained, but may in time be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted: as I ſignified cap. 11. n. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Now concerning the principall aſſumption n. 1. The ordinances which &amp;c. I anſwer, that it is neither cleere in it ſelfe, nor proued by <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> For euery precept of the Apoſtle, the keeping whereof deſerueth commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: it is not therefore a ſauing truth. Obedience to any commandement, or aduiſe of an Apoſtle touching but a rite or ceremony: yea the ſmalleſt matter that can be imagined, though it be no ſauing truth, deſerueth due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation: and <hi>Bellermin</hi> hath nothing elſe in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation that may be applied to the proofe of that point.</p>
            <p>But ſay we grant <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that the precepts ſignified verſe. 2. are ſauing truths. (as we may doe with great likely hood, vnderſtanding thereby the doctrine deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the former part of the Epiſtle to that 11. Chapter.) What will it auaile him, ſeeing the aſſumption then will conuince the propoſition of falſehood, becauſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is there written? Therefore this ſecond argument is to as ſmall purpoſe, as the former.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21008:36"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I come to the third argument in the ſame place.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thoſe things which the Apoſtle diſpoſed,</hi> 1. Cor. 11. 34. <note place="margin">Bellar. de verbo Dei non ſcripto. lib. 4. cap. 5. ſect. alteram quaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em.</note> 
                  <hi>are contained in tradition; for we find them not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any where.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But the things he there diſpoſed were ſauing truth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truth is contained in tradition.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Both the faults of the former propoſition are in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; firſt, that he taketh it for granted, that whatſoeuer the Apoſtles taught is recorded: which we alwaies denie. Secondly, that he ſaith confidently, theſe things are not written, and yet knowes not what they are: ſo that he may find them, and not know of it.</p>
            <p>Let vs paſſe by the propoſition: yet will <hi>Bellarmine</hi> come ſhort of his concluſion, becauſe the aſſumption is full of doubt; for how will he be able to proue that the things diſpoſed by the Apoſtle, were ſauing truth. He confeſſeth that ſome of them were matters belonging to rits &amp; ceremonies: but he telleh vs, with all that <hi>Catholiks worthily thinke that he deliuered alſo ſome greater matters, concerning the ordination of Miniſters, the ſacrifice of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the matter and forme of other Sacraments:</hi> and hee addeth, that <hi>The hereticks cannot diſproue them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That we may the better iudge of theſe worthy thoughts of <hi>Bellarmins</hi> Catholickes: we will ſet his reaſon in frame.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer Catholickes worthily thinke, and hereticks cannot diſproue, that is to be holder. for true.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>But that the Apoſtles diſpoſed of thoſe weightie matters Catholickes worthily thinke, and the hereticks cannot diſproue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Therefore that the Apoſtles diſpoſed of thoſe weightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it is to be holden for truth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A ſtout argument, and well worthy ſuch Catholickes who ſeeth not the abſurditie of the maior? Truth is not to be meaſured by their affirmation or conceite, and our vnableneſſe to diſproue, but by the adaequation or full agreement of the thing,, and our apprehenſion of it. For a man then onely ſpeaketh the truth of a thing,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21008:37"/> when hee ſpeaketh as the thing is indeede.</p>
            <p>But the aſſumption preſumeth we cannot diſproue it. That were hard. Why ſhould not our ſaying, we thinke he did not meane thoſe matters, be as good a diſproofe of it, as their ſaying you thinke he did, is a proofe? Such an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers are good enough for ſuch arguments. But ſurely me thinketh, we may bring ſome likelyhood of reaſon for our opinion. For who would imagine that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would ſpend ſo many lines as he doth in this chapter, about matters of ſo ſmall importance, as long haire, and bare heads, which were not for the perpetuall practiſe of the Church, as experience ſheweth: and put off mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſo great weight till his comming to them, which might haue been neuer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> And that they may not ſay, we conjecture this without any likelihood; as <hi>Bellarmins</hi> Catholiks worthily doe, let them heare what <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith upon the place. <hi>He</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Homil. 28. ad 1. Cor. 11.</note> 
               <hi>meaneth either ſome other things, or the ſame that he hath mentioned. For ſeeing it was likely that they would bring other caſes and he could not redreſſe althings by letters: Let thoſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I haue admoniſhed you of be obſerued; and if any other thing need redreſſe, let is be referred till my comming. He ſpeaketh</hi> (as I ſaid) <hi>either of the ſame thing, or ſome matter not greatly urgent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſpeaketh</hi> (ſaith Theophilact) <hi>of ſome other faults of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Theophilact. ad 1. Cor. 11.</note> 
               <hi>theirs, which had need of correcting, or of ſome which he had mentioned. It is likely</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſome men are praparing to defend themſelues againſt that which I haue ſaid, but in the meane time let thom obſerue that I haue charged them to keepe,</hi> ad 1. Cor 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When he had written of thoſe things that were more neceſſary, he reſerueth the reſt, for his praeſence with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Interlinear gloſſe expoundeth it thus: <hi>Other things concerning the Sacrament I will order when I come; but you might not be without direction for thoſe things that I haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</hi> ad 1. Cor. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Other things</hi> (ſaith Lombard) <hi>which perteine to order in</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21008:37"/> 
               <hi>the ſame Sacrament. I will order when I come.</hi> ad 1. Cor. 11. <hi>Other things which are not of ſo great danger, I will order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reſence.</hi> Thomas ad 1. Cor. 11.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of ſome other Arguments of</hi> Bellarmine <hi>to the ſame purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>LET vs ſee if <hi>Bellarmines</hi> fourth reaſon be any better then the former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which the Apoſtle commanded the Theſſalonians to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellar. ubi ſupra Sect. <hi>tertium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>keepe,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 2. 15. <hi>is contained in tradition: for it was not written, but deliuered by word of mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which the Apoſtle commanded the Theſſalouians to keepe, was a ſauing faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truth is contained in tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There is no end of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> begging. We muſt deny as before, that whatſoeuer the Apoſtles taught is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and come to poſteritie.</p>
            <p>To the propoſition I anſwer in particular, that being vnderſtood of that time when the Apoſtle writ that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, it is true: he had then deliuered ſome things by word of mouth, and not written them: and thoſe hee commandeth them to keepe. But what proofe can <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> make, that thoſe things were not written afterwards?</p>
            <p>The aſſumption is not eaſily to be proued, that thoſe things were ſauing truth. Why doth not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tell vs what they were? Me thinks he dareth not ſo much as gueſſe at them: otherwiſe he would let vs know at the leaſt, what his Catholickes worthily take them to be. Would any man dally thus in a matter of faith, to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued vpon paine of damnation?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will make amends for the want of weight in his reaſons, by the number of them: and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21008:38"/> his fift thus to bee deliuered. <note place="margin">Bellar. ubi ſupra ſect. quaitam.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which was committed to</hi> Timothy, 1. Tim. 6. 20. <hi>and</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 1. 2. <hi>is contained in tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which was there committed to</hi> Timothy, <hi>is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 20. 2. Tim. 2. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truth is contained in tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he beggeth againe as before: but wee cannot grant, that whatſoeuer the Apoſtles preached, is remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon record to poſteritie.</p>
            <p>If that were granted: yet ſhould I thinke the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition no ſufficient warrant for an Article of faith. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> offereth proofe of it on this maner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which</hi> Timothy <hi>had heard of Saint</hi> Paul, 1. Tim. 6. 20. <hi>and</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 1. 2, <hi>and was to deliuer to faithfull men able to teach other alſo, that is contained in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But that which was committed to</hi> Timothy, 1. Tim. 6. 20. <hi>and</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 1. 2, <hi>he had heard of Saint</hi> Paul, <hi>and was to deliuer to faithfull men able to teach other alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore that which was committed to</hi> Timothy, 1. Tim. 6. 20. <hi>and</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 1. 2, <hi>is contained in tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Leaſt wee ſhould deny the firſt part or Propoſition of this Syllogiſme, becauſe the things ſo delivered, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in charge by the Apoſtle, might be matter for the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent vſe of the Church, and ſuch as needed not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes knowne, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> telleth us, that by thoſe things ſo heard, and ſo to be committed, <hi>the vnderſtanding of the ſenſe of the ſcriptures, and other doctrine is ſignified:</hi> ſo that the whole force of his Argument lyeth in this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he never offereth to proue. Therefore vnleſſe we will take his bare word for proofe, wee are as farre to ſeeke, as we were before. Now that we haue no reaſon to doe ſo, I thinke it may appeare by thoſe things, which I will now propound to the conſideration of all reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21008:38"/>
            <p>Firſt then, I would know o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> whether by <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſenſe,</hi> he meane generall rules for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of it, or the ſenſe of particular places? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I demaund whether he deliuered to him the ſenſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> euery place of Scripture, or of ſome onely? Whether he anſwer this or that; I aske thirdly: what is become of thoſe rules and expoſitions? How will he proue to vs, that they haue beene continued from time to time till now? If they haue not beene continued, what haue wee to do with them, who diſpute onely of ſuch traditions as are in the poſſeſſion, and vſe of the preſent Church?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, is it likely, euen in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> iudgement, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would take vpon him to inſtruct <hi>Timothy</hi> in the ſenſe of any place of Scripture, when as the office of interpreting the Scripture is committed by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent to the Church, that is (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it) to <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſours? Did he meane am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly to vſurpe <hi>Peters</hi> office, or to ſend him to <hi>Peter</hi> or his ſucceſſours, to learne of them whether the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation he had giuen were true or no. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Touching the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the firſt Syllogiſme, that <hi>Thoſe thinges which were committed to Timothy, were ſauing truths: Bellarmine</hi> ſaith nothing: which argueth that he knew not what to ſay. What reaſon haue we then to imagine that they were ſauing truths, or that this argument concludeth any thing for the doctrine of the Councell of Trent concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing traditions?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> There is yet one argument more in the ſame fift chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thus to be concluded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe things which</hi> Iohn <hi>had to write,</hi> 2. Ioh. 11, <hi>and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bellar. ubi ſupra Sect. ultimum teſtimonium.</note> 3. Ioh. 14. <hi>are contained in tradition; for he ſaith, he would not write them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But thoſe things which he had then to write, were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing truths taught by the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truths taught by the Apostles are contained in tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am inforced here alſo to repeate my former anſwer:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21008:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21008:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21008:40"/> that <hi>Bella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mine</hi> ſtill takes it for granted, that whatſoeuer the Apoſtles taught is continued to poſteritie; which we denie: and no papiſt can proue.</p>
            <p>His aſſumption or minor is to weake to beare vp the weight of an Article of faith, vnleſſe he be able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> certainly what the things were which the Apoſtle would not write: and to whom hee did, or at the leaſt, that hee did afterward deliuer them to ſome body, from whom the Church hath receiued them. Till we know what they were, how ſhall we be ſure they were part of the ſauing truth?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of two other arguments of Bellarmine.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> VVEE haue done with the fift Chapter: and are now to examine two arguments, ſet downe chap. 4, the former I frame thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That there are Scriptures: that theſe we haue he they is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Bellar de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei non ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to cap. 4 Sect. quarto, quinto, Soxio.</note> 
               <hi>contained in tradition; For we cannot find them in the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But that there are Scriptures; that theſe wee haue are they, is part of ſauing truth taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truthes taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, are contained in tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It hath appeared by my anſwer to <hi>Bellarmines</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he can find no place of Scripture, that ſendeth vs to tradition for any part of ſauing truth, taught by our Lord or his Apoſtles; Wee might therefore conclude, that there are no ſuch traditions, without troubling our ſelues any further. But that we may dit vp the mouths of the Papiſts, wee will beſtow a little time and paines in theſe arguments.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21008:40"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If there had beene no more intended by the Councell of Trent in the decree touching tradition, but to ſignifie that theſe three points are contained in tradition, the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger had not beene great: for then both the number and the particulars had been determined; but the Papiſts by vertue of that Article take authoritie to thruſt what they liſt vpon the Church, and warrant it by tradition.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thus much to the argument in generall: Particularly I anſwer, that the firſt part of it and the proofe thereof, ſuppoſe that thoſe two propoſitions, <hi>There are Scriptures: Theſe we haue be they,</hi> are formally, that is expreſly contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either in the Scriptures or tradition; But this ſay we is falſe: they are contained formally in neither; where then ſhall we finde them? Radically and originally in the Scriptures themſelues: which of themſelues afford iuſt occaſion to all men to conceiue, both that <hi>There are Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and that <hi>Theſe are they;</hi> They are contained formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the apprehenſion of euery mans vnderſtanding that beleeueth them: and that this beleife is diuine faith, not humane coniecture it appeareth, becauſe it is wrought in men by a ſpeciall prouidence of God, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth and draweth men to acknowledge the things to be as they are in themſelues: and is farther grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diuine authoritie, vertually affirming that they are both true indeed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And yet wee make not a priuate ſpirit the ground or rule of our faith, or the iudge to determine what is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith, what is not; As <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſlandereth vs: and <note place="margin">Bellar de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei non ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lib. 3. cap. 5. Sect. Norum &amp; cap. 9. ſect. quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> after him Mr. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſher,</hi> and other. But wee onely attribute to that ſpeciall prouidence the office of in lightening, and mouing the vnderſtanding in lightened, to giue aſſent to the bookes of Scripture, that they are the word of God: as indeed and truth they are. Now to this aſſent it moueth vs by many reaſons fit and effectuall for ſuch a worke: as namely by the continuall conſent and teſtimonie of the Church: by the matter deliuered in the bookes them ſelues: by the ſtile or maner of deliuering it, and the like
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21008:41"/> as diuers of our diuines haue ſhewed at large; and that this aſſent of ours is a true faith, it is very manifeſt: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it conceiueth of the thing deliuered as in truth it is: which is the very rule of truth, and wherein the nature of truth conſiſteth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The aſſumption is falſe. The laſt propoſition, is not part of ſauing truth taught by our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Neither all nor any of the Apoſtles (for ought appeareth in the word) did euer ſet downe a Catalogue of the Bookes of the New or Old Teſtament: neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede was it poſſible for any of them to doe it but <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> who out liued them all, and writt after them all. As for <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> he neither might nor could doe it, becauſe that was onely <hi>Peters</hi> office or his ſucceſſors, to declare which were Scriptures, and which were not, as we learned out of <hi>Bellar.</hi> Chap. 3. 11. 9. <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar. ubi ſupra ſect, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nique.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſecond and laſt argument lieth thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Propoſition, There is no word of God beſides that which is written, is contained in tradition not written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This propoſition is a ſauing truth taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore ſome ſauing truth taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is contained in tradition not written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt it is to be conſidered, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bringeth this aſſumption as a propoſition of ours, and from thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth for the Church of Rome againſt vs; For if hee brought it as his owne, and acknowledged by him for true, he ſhould thereby gaine ſay the Councell of Trent, affirming that <hi>There is ſome part of the word of God contained in tradition, which is not to be found in the Scriptures.</hi> But in this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth vs wrong: for although we ſay, that there is no word of God but that which is contained in the Scriptures, as <note n="a" place="margin">Rellar. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei lib. 4. cap. 3. Sect. adipſi.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> alleageth out of <note n="b" place="margin">Caluin. Inſtit. lib, 4. cap. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Caluin;</hi> yet we ſay uot, that this propoſition is a ſauing truth taught by Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles: neither indeed need we ſay ſo; For by that propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we only deny that which the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell affirmeth, and ſet it downe as a contradictory thereto:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21008:41"/> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe in the place for enamed bringeth it to the ſame end. The reaſon of our deniall is, that the Scripture doth no where ſend vs to tradition, nor hath any word to that purpoſe; as hath appeared in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſputation. And this reaſon is very ſufficient: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing is to be receiued for an Article of faith, but that which is taught in the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The like anſwer is to be made to the propoſition. If it be true in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> iudgement, then the doctrine of the Church of Rome in his iudgement is ſalfe. For the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent teacheth, that <hi>There is ſome word of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in tradition;</hi> but this propoſition affirmes, that <hi>There is no word of God beſides that which is written.</hi> If <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> would father it vpon vs, he accuſeth vs falſly. For we neuer ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor thought that that propoſition was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in tradition; but perhaps he thinketh it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vpon that wee ſay: but in ſo thinking, hee thinkes idly; for we doe no more hereby, but denie that which they ſay: and neither do nor neede affirme that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained either in the Scriptures, or in tradition. It is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough for vs in matter of faith, to refuſe whatſoeuer is not taught in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> But it may be ſaid, that this propoſition, <hi>There is no word of God beſides that which is written,</hi> is either true or falſe; we grant it: becauſe it is certainely true, that in euerie contradiction properly ſo called, the one propoſition is true, the other falſe. What of this? It will farder be ſaid; If it be falſe, then the contradictory to it which we hold, is true. We grant this too: what more? If this be true, it is contained either in the Scripture, or in tradition. This we denie; It may be true, and yet contained in neither of them; For the truth of this propoſition is not poſitiue, whereby one thing is affirmed of, or ioyned to another: but negatiue, by which one thing is denied of, or ſeuered from another. Now propoſitions of this kinde are then true, when the things comprehended in them are indeed ſeuered the one from the other: for then the propoſition
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21008:42"/> ſpeaketh of the thing as it is. Therefore it is enough to make this negatiue propoſition true, that the Scripture is ſilent in that which they affirme, and doth not ioyne <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 5.</note> them together, as they doe. And this is the ground of thoſe negatiue diſputations wee find in the Scriptures <note place="margin">P. Iewels anſw. to D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Coles ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. let. O. P.</note> eſpecially, <hi>To which of the Angells ſaid be, &amp;c.</hi> He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to ſee more of this, may reade the reuerend Biſhop <hi>Iewel</hi> in his anſwer to Dr. <hi>Cole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> I ſhould now goe on according to the order followed in the Councell of Trent, to examine the reſt of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles ſet downe by me chap. 11. num. 3. But for this time I thinke it enough that I haue debated theſe two que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions: becauſe if theſe proue falſe, as I truſt they haue done, all the other differences betwixt vs and the Church of Rome, will eaſily be decided to the confirmation of the truth we maintaine, and the ouerthrow of their falſe and erroneous faith. I haue alreadie in another diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Latine, diſcouered and proued the erroneouſneſſe of the faith of that Church in the ſeuenth, and tenth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the eleuenth Chapter before mentioned, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace and iuſtification. The like I will doe in the reſt, if it pleaſe God to giue me opportunitie and abilitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>An anſwer to thoſe things which the Church of Rome bringeth againſt the neceſsitie of ſeparating from it.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ALthough the point propounded by me to be diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is ſufficiently proued by that which hath paſt: and all men may ſee a neceſſitie of ſeparating from the Church of Rome: yet that the truth may be the more cleere, and all mens conſciences the better ſatiſfied, and fortified againſt the deuiſes of the Romiſh ſeducers: I
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21008:42"/> haue thought good to examine two principall motiues of theirs, by which they miſ-lead many that are ſimple or careleſſe; and in handling of them, I will take the ſame courſe that hetherto I haue followed, for the more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and certaintie in iudging what is true, what falſe.</p>
            <p>The former of the two is this:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Euery man muſt receiue his faith by the teaching of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it may appeare what force there is in this to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clud any thing for the Church of Rome againſt the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion hetherto diſputed, I will apply it to the matter in queſtion, and anſwer to it accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They that muſt receiue their faith by the teaching of the Church of Rome, muſt ioyne in faith with that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery man muſt receiue his faith by the teaching of the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore euery man muſt ioyne in faith with the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propoſition or firſt part of this reaſon I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for true: becauſe the teaching of the Church of Rome giueth being to the faith of that Church.</p>
            <p>The aſſumption is falſe, being grounded vpon that falſe foundation, that <hi>The Pope of Rome is to feede the whole Church as Peters ſucceſſour, by determining what is matter of faith, what is not.</hi> But this appeared to be manifeſtly falſe, chap. 8. and 10. wherein I propounded and handled the queſtion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond deuiſe is commonly deliuered by way of queſtion. <hi>Where was your Church before Luther?</hi> Now this queſtion implyeth a negation; as if they ſhould ſay: <hi>The Proteſtants Church was not before Luther.</hi> This muſt be applied to the point in queſtion, after this ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery man muſt ioyne in faith either with the Church of Rome, or with the Proteſtant Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But no man may ioyne in faith with the Proteſtants Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21008:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore euery man muſt ioyne in faith with the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the propoſition paſſe for true: to which we may iuſtly adde an aſſumption contrary to theirs; No man may ioyne in faith with the Church of Rome: and this aſſumption is alreadie made good by the foregoing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, through this whole treatiſe: which hath ſhewed that the faith of the Church of Rome is falſe and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But to anſwer directly to their aſſumption, we ſay it is vtterly falſe, and the contrary to it euidently true, that <hi>Euery man is bound to ioyne in faith with the Proteſtants Church.</hi> For our faith is nothing elſe but <hi>Euery article or propoſition to be aſſented to, or beleeued as true vpon the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God the reuealer of them by his holy ſeruants the Prophets, and Apoſtles.</hi> The Articles which we aſſent to or beleeue in this ſort, are either expreſſely ſet downe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in direct words, ſo that the ſenſe of them cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be doubted of: or elſe gathered, and concluded from ſuch places by neceſſarie conſequence: ſo that if the one be true, the other muſt needs be true alſo. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer propoſition is not of this nature, we allow not for an article of faith, how likely ſoeuer it ſeeme to be. Now in this faith of ours there can be no danger: ſeeing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer propoſition is plainely expreſſed in the Scripture, or neceſſarily concluded from it, is vndoubtedly the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine reuelation, which is the onely foundation of true faith.</p>
            <p>More particularly I ſay touching the ſaid aſſumption, that it muſt be vnderſtood of the Proteſtants faith, ſo far forth as it differeth from the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> elſe by it they ſhould diſſwade men from the faith of their owne Church.</p>
            <p>Beſides, It is to be conſidered that this aſſumption ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, that the Proteſtants haue a faith oppoſite to the faith of the Church of Rome; Which is vtterly falſe. All the oppoſition we make to them is, by refuſing their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21008:43"/> faith, not by deliuering any of our owne, and by anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to their arguments: ſo that we hold the negatiue part of the contradiction, in all points, wherein we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from them, although in ſome we adde a contrarie affirmatiue, where the Scripture affirmeth that which they denie. For example, they ſay <hi>The Pope is Gods Vicar.</hi> This we oppoſe by ſaying, that <hi>The diuine reuelation doth not teach vs, that the Pope is Gods Vicar.</hi> Againe, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer this for an Article of faith: that <hi>Concupiſcence in the regenerate, is not properly ſinne.</hi> To this we anſwer by way of oppoſition as to the former: <hi>The diuine reuelation doth not ſay, that Concupiſcence in the regenerate is not properly ſin;</hi> Yea in this point we ſay further: the Scripture ſaith it is properly ſinne: but our oppoſition to them in this point ſtands in this, that the Scripture doth not ſay it is not properly ſinne, ſo that though there were no word to the contrarie of it in Scripture, yet that propoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on of theirs were vtterly falſe. By which it is manifeſt, that in thoſe things wherein we diſſent from them, we haue not arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith contrarie to the articles of faith which they propound: but onely deny, that <hi>Thoſe they would thruſt vpon vs are articles of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> If any man obiect (as <hi>Stapleton</hi> and <hi>Wright</hi> doe,) that <hi>Our religion is negatiue;</hi> we anſwer, that if they meane we hold no articles of faith which are affirmatiue, they charge vs vntruely; for we conſent with them in many affirmatiue articles of faith. As for thoſe points wherein we diſſent from them, it is no fault in vs to hold the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue; for there is no other way for vs to oppoſe the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours they bring for matters of faith, but by denying them to be matters of faith.</p>
            <p>So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this is that they auouch in the former aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No man may ioyne in faith with the Proteſtants Churches, in thoſe points wherein they diſſent from the Faith of the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is, becauſe the faith of the Proteſtants in thoſe points is falſe; which they thus proue:</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21008:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The true faith hath been profeſſed ſo publikely in all ages ſince the Apostles, that the profeſſors of it from age to age may be named.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Proteſtants faith hath not been ſo publikely profeſſed in all ages ſince the Apoſtles, that the profeſſors of it from age to age may be named.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the Proteſtants faith is not the true faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Before I anſwer directly to the parts of this Syllogiſme, I hold it needfull to note a few things concerning the reaſon in generall. The firſt is, that in this queſtion wee inquire not of ſuch profeſſours onely as our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles were, who deliuered the Articles of faith by way of reuelation: but of ſuch as haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and profeſt thoſe articles, as they haue beene ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of that which they reuealed. Secondly, it is worth the doing, to conſider a little way of geſſe, what the reaſon ſhould be why the Papiſts are ſo loath to make tryall of their faith by the Scriptures, and cry ſo loud for a catalogue or regiſter of the names of ſuch as haue from time to time beleeued as now we do. This may well ſeeme ſtrange to all men, who vnderſtand that the diuine reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is a moſt faithfull record, and moſt certaine rule in all matters of faith: ſo that whatſoeuer is agreeable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is a part of true faith: whatſoeuer differeth from it either poſitiuely by affirming that which is not reuealed, or negatiuely by denying that which is reuealed, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, and may not be taken for an article of faith. As for a beadroll of names, who knoweth not that it muſt needes be made out of humaine ſtorie. <hi>Wher as Diuine and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible faith is not built upon deduction out of humane hiſtorie, but diuene reuelation;</hi> as is well obſerued by the learned &amp; reuerend D. <hi>Featly</hi> And how can that be any foundation of diuine faith, when it is not diuine authoritie, nor free from errour: but humane onely, and ſubiect to errour: yea among all kindes of humane authoritie of leaſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? Our of doubt then the Papiſts would neuer haue purſued this courſe ſo eagerly, but for ſome eſpeciall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21008:44"/> aduantage to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe, which in all likely hood is this; that they ſaw well enough, it was not for their religion to abide the tryall by Scripture in thoſe articles of faith. But what ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah? If they refuſe the Law</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8. 20. 8</note> 
               <hi>and the teſtimonie, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Now in particular, I ſay that the propoſition is faultie diuers wayes. Firſt whereas it ſuppoſeth that the true faith hath beene in all ages in the word: if they meane it hath been in the Scriptures in all ages: we grant that they ſay is true, but we adde that it is not to purpoſe; for our queſtion is not of faith as it is reuealed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but as it is gathered out of them, and particularly beleeued; and in this latter ſence, we denie that the true faith hath been in all ages.</p>
            <p>For proofe of our deniall we alleage the experience of all ages: by which it is manifeſt, that ſome articles of faith haue been obſeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed and concluded out of the Scriptures from time to time, and were not all known and beleeued for articles of ſaith at once. I may bring for inſtance thoſe great points debated and determined in the 4 firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells. For certainely if <hi>The god-head of our bleſſed Sauiour, and the holy Ghoſt, the diſtinction of the diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine natures of our Lord Ieſus, the Vnitie of his perſon,</hi> had <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> bin reſolutely holden in the Church for articles of faith: <hi>Arius, Macedonius, Eutyches,</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius</hi> would not haue durſt to ſpeake of them ſo wickedly and heretically as they did; neither would the Church haue aſſembled Councells to aduiſe of the points, but haue caſt out thoſe wretches as enemies of the faith. The like might be ſaid of <hi>Pelagius</hi> touching grace: and of many other points of no ſmall importance.</p>
            <p>To come nearer to this our age, there is no Papiſt of any reading and iudgement, but will confeſſe that diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs propoſitions in tholate Councell of Trent, which ended ſince I was borne, were neuer receiued for articles of faith, till they were neuer receiued for articles of faith, till they were propounded for ſuch by that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21008:45"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Secondly, to grant them as much as they deſire; I yet except againſt their propoſition as falſe: becauſe there is no neceſſitie, that the being of true faith, and ſuch a profeſſion thereof muſt alwayes goe together; For ſuch a publike profeſſion of faith, is neither of the eſſence of true faith, as a reaſonable ſoule is of the eſſence of a man: nor proceedeth from the eſſence thereof, as the faculty of ſpeech doth from the eſſence of man: neither are they lincked inſeparably together by any ordianance of God, as faith and iuſtification are. The two former I am not out of doubt all Papiſts will grant; If they fly to the laſt, let them ſhew the record or deed, wherein that coniunction of true faith, and ſuch a publike profeſſion of it is inrolled and ingroſſed. Will they tell vs I know not what goodly matters of the viſibilitie of the Church? what is that but to beg the queſtion? For we denie that, as no leſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and vntrue, then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The aſſumption alſo is falſe, which auoucheth ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently that:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The profeſſours of the Proteſtants faith in ſuch things As they diſſent from the Church of Rome in, cannot be ſhewed in all ages from time to time ſince our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we call for a proofe of this: they bid vs ſhew a bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll of their names that were profeſſours of our faith; what if we cannot? will they conclude thereupon that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done? there may be a Catalogue, though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhew it; Which cannot ſeeme ſtrange to any man that ſhall conſider, that the Papiſts had for many yeares, yea, ages the whole ſway &amp; command of Chriſtendome, and laboured all they could to make away (if it had been poſſible,) not onely the writings, but the memorie of all ſuch as made any kind of oppoſition to their doctrine or proceedings; Yet by the gracious &amp; mighty prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God it hath come to paſſe, that the regiſters of their own bloudy perſecutors haue by the worthy paines of ſom of our writers, afforded the world a view of the names, of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny holy Martyrs &amp; confeſſours, which from time to time
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21008:45"/> haue refuſed as we do now, to acknowledge many of the points wherein we diſſent from the Church of Rome: and it cannot be looked for, that wee ſhould ſhew that all of them haue been denied, becauſe many of them were firſt bred and hatched in the late Councell of Trent, and were neuer articles of faith till then. Wherefore to returne to my firſt concluſion: ſince the faith of the Church of Rome is erroneous, both in the foundation of it: which is the authoritie of the Church, and in many particular articles thereof; I may boldly affirme, that it is to be ſhunned as a perilous rocke, whereon many haue ſuffered ſhipwrack of their eternall ſaluation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the faith of the Church of Rome is to refuſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of damnation.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> VVHen I firſt deliuered the propoſition I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to handle, (that there might be no igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by errour, nor ſhifting by willfull miſtaken) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to declare the meaning of the termes, in which I propounded my queſtion; but becauſe I purpoſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the matter in two ſeuerall diſputations, I forbare to expound the laſt words, till I ſhould come to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar debating of the ſecond point. Now I am to enter vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and muſt therefore ſhew what I meane by thoſe words, <hi>Vpon paine of damnation:</hi> and then proue, that the faith of the Church of Rome is to be refuſed vpon ſo grieuous a penaltie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thoſe words <hi>Vpon paine of damnation,</hi> are not ſo to bee vnderſtood, as if I tooke vpon me to pronounce ſentence of condemnation againſt all that beleeue as the Church of Rome teacheth: but I would thereby giue all men to vnderſtand, that the beleeuing of that doctrine as matter
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21008:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21008:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:21008:47"/> of faith, is a thing in it ſelfe damnable, and ſuch as maketh a man liable to damnation. How it ſhall fall out with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men in the euent, I neither know, nor meane to enquire. Onely I ſay againe, that their miſ-beliefe is a ſinne, which ſetteth them in the ſtate of damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Now hauing proued alreadie that their faith is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, I ſhall not neede to make many words about the point. For the Church of Rome againſt which I diſpute. holdeth it for a ruled caſe, that <hi>an erroneous faith is damnable.</hi> Wherefore elſe doe they thunder out ſo many <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai. 8. 20.</note> curſes in the Councell of Trent, againſt all that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue otherwiſe of the matters of faith determined by that Councell, then is therein decreed? Notwithſtanding that I may the better perſwade all men to keepe good watch, for feare they be ſuddenly ſurprized, or vnawares intrapt by the great army of locuſts, the Prieſts and Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, which haue almoſt couered the Land from ſea to ſea, I will beſtow a little paines to giue them warning of the danger.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> There are two wayes by which ſinne leadeth a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to the ſtate of damnation: the one is the deſert or fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it hath to procure damnation: the other is the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all meriting or deſeruing of damnation. Into the former, ſinne caſteth a man off it ſelfe. Into the latter he falleth, as by ſinne, ſo by the ordinance or decree of God, who hath layd a penalty of damnation upon it. Out of this I raiſe this diſputation againſt receiuing the faith of the Romiſh Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which maketh a man vncleane in Gods ſight, hath a fitneſſe to procure damnation. For vncleane things are vnmeete for the preſence of God: and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are meete for damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the faith of the Church of Rome maketh a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is erroneous in ſo high a nature, that it maketh a man guiltie of treaſon againſt God, by inſtalling the Pope in the Throane of God, giuing him power and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21008:47"/> authoritie to determine as a iudge what is matter of faith, what not, without commiſſion or warrant from God, as I haue ſhewed in the former part of this diſputation; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they onely giue him authoritie to interprete the Scriptures: but alſo allow him to ſet vp a forge, where he hammers what he liſt, and venteth it to be receiued vpon paine of damnation, for the word of the euer liuing <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 4.</note> God. What is it <hi>To ſit in the Temple of God, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he is God,</hi> if this be not? And are not they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries to this high treaſon that acknowledge this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and yeeld obedience to it? How can it then reaſonably be denied, that there is a worthineſſe and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the faith of the Church of Rome to procure dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? hereupon it followeth, that euery one that ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in faith with the Church of Rome is lyable to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> There remaineth nothing now but the ordinance or decree of God, to appoint damnation as a puniſhment of this ſinne, according to the deſert thereof: but that was paſſed long ſince by the Lord himſelfe, <hi>You ſhall put no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the word which I command you.</hi> The penaltie is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 2 &amp; 12 30. Revel. 21. 18.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſhall adde to thoſe things, God ſhall adde to him the plagues that are written in this Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But more plaine. <hi>The Lord ſhall ſend them strong deluſions, that they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould beleeue lyes, that all they might be damned which belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not the truth.</hi> Behold the Lord wrappeth them vp in damnation, by his ſentence that beleeue lyes: (that is) falſe and erroneous doctrine not agreeable to the truth, which they ought to beleeue. What is wanting then to make the faith of the Church of Rome damnable, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours thereof lyable to damnation: when both the thing it ſelfe deſerueth it, and the Lord hath decreed, that they which beleeue it, ſhould haue according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> I might, as our writers commonly doe, adde to that which hath beene ſaid, diuers foule and groſſe errors, which ſeeme more ſpecially to touch the glory of God,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21008:48"/> and ſecretly to vndermine the very foundation of our ſaluation: namely the Mediatorſhip of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt. But this (as I take it) will more plainly appeare, and be more throughly inforced againſt them, in the particular handling of the ſeuerall Articles; to which I reſerue it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Neither will I enter into the common way of prouing popery to be damnable, becauſe it is Antichriſtianiſme; much hath beene diſputed by our men to this purpoſe: and it is like enough that much more may, and will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their diſputations. But the controuerſie is long, and requireth more time then I can now afford it: onely this I will ſay for the preſent, that (as his Maieſtie hath prudently obſerued) there is no Church, State, nor man that hath beene ſince the penning of the Reuelation, to whom thoſe things foretold by the Apoſtle from the mouth of the Lord Ieſus, can in any reaſonable ſort agree, but the Church and Pope of Rome alone. And it is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt reaſon to imagin, that the Lord Ieſus would direct <hi>Iohn</hi> to ſpend ſo many words in deliuering prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for ſome three yeares and a halfe in the end of the world, and leaue ſo many yeares betwixt vnſpoken of, wherein ſuch ſtrange matters haue befallen the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> It is manifeſt, that the Hiſtorie is prophetically con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the firſt 300 yeares at the leaſt: and of that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemeth not much to concerne them, the Papiſts make no great doubt; he that will take the paines to reade the whole aduiſedly, may eaſily diſcerne that our Lord continueth his diſcourſe to his beloued Diſciple, of ſuch things as were to fall out to the very end of the world. I forbeare to ſhew how vnlikely, (that I may ſpeake moſt fauourably of the point, becauſe it hath ſome col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable allowance from antiquitie) I will not ſay how vnpoſſible it is, that any man ſhould imagine hee can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chriſtians, as Antichriſt (by their conceite) muſt doe: or force them generally to denie the Lord Ieſus, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21008:48"/> take himſelfe to be either God, or any man ſent from God. This appeared plainely in that couſening com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannion <hi>Mahomet:</hi> who yet was not ſo mad, as (in their opinion) Antichriſt will be, to require that all men ſhould acknowledge and adore him for God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>A concluſion of the whole Treatiſe by way of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſeparate from the Church of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>I Said a little more in that matter of Antichriſt, then I purpoſed to doe when I entred into it: for it was my meaning onely to touch it by the way: and that rather becauſe I thought it would bee looked for, then that I found it greatly neceſſarie; for what neede I ſeeke any other reaſons to inforce a neceſſitie of ſeparating from the Church of Rome, then thoſe I haue already alleaged? Therefore I will now adde a few words of exhortation, and ſo end both the readers, and mine owne labour.</p>
            <p>It is reported by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> &amp; by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> of the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <note place="margin">Irenaeus contra hareſ. lib. 3. c. 3. Euſeb. eccle. hiſt. lib. 3. cap. 25.</note> Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that when he ſpied <hi>Ceri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thus</hi> the hereticke in the bath where he was, he made all the haſt he could to be gone, thinking it dangerous to be vnder the ſame roofe with him. Yea the very Heathen (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) being at ſea in a ſore ſtorme, were much afraie they ſhould <note place="margin">Tully de natura Deorum lib. 3.</note> haue beene caſt away, becauſe they had <hi>Diagoras</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt abord amomg them. I would to God ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants were as charie of their ſoules, as, (I ſay not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) but the Heathen of their bodies: and had as much care to prouide for their eternall ſaluation, as they had to procure their temporall ſafetie; neither the Apoſtle, nor the Heathen had any thing to doe with the impietie of <hi>Ceri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thus</hi> or <hi>Diagoras:</hi> and yet both he and they doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome euill might befall them, becauſe they were in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21008:49"/> in the companie of ſuch prophane wretches. And can any Proteſtant imagine that he may be free from danger, though he ioyne in faith with the Pope of Rome? It coſt <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> deare, though he were otherwiſe a good King, for going to warre with <hi>Ahab</hi> againſt a common enemy. What ſaid <hi>Hauani</hi> the Seer? <hi>Wouldest thou helpe the wicked,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 19. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and loue them that hate the Lord? therefore for this thing the wrath of the Lord is vpon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then may they looke for, who like the <hi>Ladice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3. 16.</note> are <hi>luke-warme neyther bote nor cold,</hi> altogther indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferent, whether they be Papiſts or Proteſtants? They are in better caſe, yet not ſafe neither, who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that Poperie is erroneous, but doe not thinke it ſo dangerous a matter to be a Papiſt, that a man neede flee out of the Romiſh Church, as <hi>Lot</hi> did oun of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> That I may plucke or thruſt theſe men out, as the Angells did <hi>Lot,</hi> I haue undertaken this diſcoverie of the danger, by labouring to informe their judgement with the knowledge of the truth. I muſt now proceed to inflame their affection with deteſtation of errour. The glory of the vnderſtanding is truth: the height of the affection zeale. To be zealous without knowledge, is to fight without armes, like the Iſraelites, that <hi>had not a ſheild nor spare amongſt fourtie thowſand of them.</hi> Iudges 5. 8. To haue knowledge without zeale, is to haue armes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out courage, as the <hi>Ephraimites</hi> had. <hi>Pſal. 78. 9. Who went up armed with bowes, but turned their backs in the day of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</hi> In this fight againſt Popery, you haue need of know ledge; becauſe your enemy is ſubtill to deceiue; of zeale, becauſe your quarrell is great. For you are to fight, not for your wiues and children onely, but alſo for your God, and your religion: not againſt an errour or two that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace your profeſſion, like a wen in a faire body: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch an heretick, as like the diſeaſe in the hart, will vndermine and ouerthrow the whole ſtate of the body.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſed his Lord and Maſter that thee might betray him; ſo the Pope of Rome vnder a ſhew of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21008:49"/> hath taken the honour of God to himſelfe, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be his factour, intendeth to rob &amp; vndo him. Will he with the ſtubborne Iewes in <hi>Mallachy</hi> aske mee wherin? I will not anſwer him as the Prophet doth, <hi>In tithes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</hi> What are tithes &amp; offerings to ſupremacy &amp; ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty? This, this is the robbery, the Sacriledge whereof we accuſe the Pope of Rome. If he had but taken from his fellow Biſhops, and appropriated to himſelfe the honour &amp; authoritie that is common to them with him, we would haue holden our peace: although this proud <hi>Haman</hi> could no way haue made recompence to the Church of Chriſt, for the loſſe ſhe ſuſtaineth thereby. Yea, though he haue with the euill ſeruaut in the Goſpell impriſoned, beaten, murdered his fellow ſeruants for doing their maſters work, we would as we haue done, in dure it with patience and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Shall I ſay more? Albeit he had maintained, as he doth, diuers foule and groſſe errours againſt the truth of God, we would haue contented our ſelues with diſſenting from him therein, without breach of the band of peace. But now ſo ſtandeth the caſe, that he hath claimed and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped the prerogatiue of the great God of heauen and earth. Should we now forbeare to ſpeake? Should we in ſuch a caſe look for commendation of modeſtie, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe? Haue we no more zeale of the glory of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, our King, our God? Hath the loue of our moſt deere Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, deſerued no more kindnes at our hands? If we could be ſo monſtrouſly vnthankfull, the very ſtones in the Church walls, and the becames in the roofes would cry out againſt vs and him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> For hath he not made himſelfe a foundation of the faith of all men, yea the next and immediate foundation of all diuine faith, ſo that nothing may be taken for matter of ſaith but vpon his authoritie? Neither doth this authority of his lay hold on vs only, which are as it were of the lower houſe, but it reacheth alſo to the vpper houſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelues; For by vertue of that commiſſion (ſaith <note place="margin">Ioh. 21. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine,) The reſt of the Apoſtles were made ſubiect to Peter,</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21008:50"/> 
               <hi>and his ſucceſſours the Biſhops of Rome.</hi> O ridiculous conceit! O preſumptious ambition! was it not enough for you to trample on the necks of other Chriſtians, many of whom were (at the leaſt) equall to the beſt of your Popes for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie, but that you may bring the Apoſtles heads vnder your Idols girdle?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Heare O heauen, and hearken O earth! The holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> liued by the record of Hiſtories, till the yeare after our Lords birth 100; Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was (as it is alſo writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) martired at Rome in the yeare 68: therefore there were 32 yeares betwixt the death of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> In theſe 32 yeares (not to reckon <hi>Linus,</hi> who is thought to haue bin Pope) there were 4 ſeuerall Biſhops of Rome, <hi>Clemens, Cletus, Anacletus,</hi> and <hi>Euariſtus.</hi> By popiſh diuinitie S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſo ſubiect to theſe ſucceſſours of <hi>Peter,</hi> that he was to receiue from them aſſurance of the truth that he deliuered: of them he was to know whether his owne Epiſtles were the word of God or not: yea whether they were his owne Epiſtles or not: they, or ſome of them were to aſſure him from God, that his Reuelation was from God, and not from the deuill: if any doubt aroſe about any ſentence in his Goſpell, Epiſtles, or Reuelation he could not know by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine faith, what the true meaning of the place was, but was to learne that of <hi>Euariſtus</hi> then Pope: whoſe office it was to deliuer an interpretation of the text to the Apoſtle, or to allow of the interpretation made by the Apoſtle, if he iudged it to be true. Poore S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was an vnderling in all this buſineſſe, the Pope was <hi>Magiſter fac totum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Moſt glorious Lord Ieſus, thou didſt vouchſafe to ſhew thine extraordinarie loue to this thy holy Apoſtle, &amp; too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt order to haue it made known to all poſterity, wouldeſt thou ſo much abaſe him, as not onely to take from him the honour thou hadeſt beſtowed vpon him, by making him inferiour to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom before he was equall in authoritie and dignitie: but alſo to appoint him to lacky, (if occaſion fell out) vpon foure Popes one after another, to learne of them what was diuine reuelation, or the word of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21008:50"/> God, what was not? Wherefore didſt thou ſolemnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thy Apoſtles, and <hi>Iohn</hi> amongſt the reſt, that thou wouldeſt ſend them the comforter, the holy Spirit, to lead them into, and to direct them in all truth? Alas it was a poore comfort for them ſo to be taught by him, that they muſt be faine to trauell or ſend to Rome, to know whether he had taught them right or no. But who can be patient in this indignity offered to the holy Spirit? Shall a wretched and ignorant man (that I ſay no worſe) ſit in iudgement to giue ſentence of thy diuine Maieſtie, whether thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired thy ſeruants with truth or no? Diddeſt thou inſtruct the Apoſtles, as the deuills amongſt the heathen did their counterfit prophets, that they either knew not what they vttered, or could not be aſſured what they meaned, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Pope like an Oracle made them vnderſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; as <hi>Daniell</hi> told <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> his dreame, and the interpretation thereof?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> If theſe things ſeeme to be, as indeed they are abſurd, monſtrous, impious, blaſphemous, what is the doctrine thinke you, vpon which they are grounded? I will repeate it againe, that all men may learne to know and deteſt ſuch fooliſh wickedneſſe and wicked folly. <hi>S. Peter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine) was made by Chriſt ordinary paſtour of the whole Church: his oſſice was to determine what was matter of faith; The Biſhops of Rome.</hi> Peters <hi>ſucceſſours, haue the ſame authoritie of ordinarie paſtourſhip which he had; Whoſoeuer will not be thus fed by</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>and his ſucceſſours, belongeth not to the ſheepefold of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> This is the arch, whereon the Popes ſupremacie is built. For the vpholding of this, all the Romiſh Clergie are in armes. If you hold not this, whatſoeuer you hold, you can be no true Roman Catholike.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> From whence ariſeth the impoſſibility of reconciliation betwixt vs and them: wee cannot bee members of their Church, but we muſt ioyn with them in this acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Papall authoritie. They cannot renounce this opinion, but they muſt withall viterly diſſolue their Church, the forme whereof (as we heard out of <hi>Bellarmine)</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:21008:51"/> conſiſteth in this very manner of gouerment. This is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, theſe the ligame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts by which the whole body of their Church is coupled and knit together. From the Pope thus feeding (that is teaching and gouerning) as from the head, all life and motion is conueyed into the reſt of that huge chaos; take away the head, all life and motion ceaſeth, and the parts fall aſunder one from another, that it can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be accounted the Church it was, nor as they hold any Church at all. We ſee the prophecie of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> fulfilled. <hi>God hath ſent theſe men ſtrong deluſions to beleeue lyes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> For what greater deluſion can there be, then for a man to beleeue that of euery Pope, that no Pope euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued of himſelfe, or of any of his ſucceſſours.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> And ſhall we notwithſtanding all this, ſtill halt betwixt two opinions? Shall we ſuffer our ſelues to be ſo ſwallowed vp by the cares of this world, that we can haue no leaſure to know what belongeth to our ſaluation? Shall wee ſo melt away in continuall voluptuouſneſſe, that we will not ſpare one houre to learne which is the right way to true happineſſe? Shall we ſo pleaſe our ſelues in wilfull igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that we deſpiſe the knowledge of truth in matter of religion? Doe theſe things concerne Preachers onely? If our fore fathers had been of that minde, the troups of holy Martyrs, that now gloriouſly follow their puiſſant &amp; victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious leader the Lord Ieſus in triumph, would haue beene very thinne; Oh that you could ſee them with your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes: How many bleſſed Saints ſhould you behold now triumphing in heauen, that were as you are, not Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, but ordinary profeſſours of the truth? Brethren de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not your owne ſoules: caſt not your ſelues away wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Are not the people to be ſaued by the ſame meanes by which the Preachers are? Is not the ſame faith in the Lord Ieſus which muſt ſaue the Miniſters, required of the people alſo? The Lord indeed hath giuen vs ſpeciall charge to ſtudie, and know the holy Scriptures; to what end think you? ſurely as for our owne comfort, ſo for your inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The affaires of the world in your ſeuerall callings draw
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21008:51"/> you away from opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtunity of ſtudie; the Lord in mercy to you, hath commanded vs to labour in it: that your want may be ſupplied by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r aboundance. Now eſpecially hee looketh for this dutie of vs, becauſe he will now eſpecially make tryall of your knowledge and conſtancy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Do you not ſee many fall dayly on your right hand, and on your left? It is not your ſtrength, but Gods mercifull prouidence that holdeth you vpright: he hath graciouſly vouchſafed to keepe you hetherto from occaſion of being ſeduced: he hath afforded you more time yet before the temptation, like an armed man ſhall aſſault you: if you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare not now for the day of battell, the enemy will ſurpriſe you are you be aware, when you ſhall not be able to make reſiſtance; Many of you ſcarce know a friend from an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, you are not able to diſcerne which be your owne colours. It is an eaſie matter to carry you into the middeſt of <hi>Dothan,</hi> while you ſeeke for the Prophet, whom you know not if you meete him. As he that walketh into the fields, where there grow as well poyſonous weeds as whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome herbs, if he know not the one from the other, may as eaſily light vpon that which ſhal kill him, as that which ſhal nouriſh him. So he that is ignorant what is true, what falſe in matters of faith, is as like to be led into errour that ſhall damne him, as to be taught truth that ſhall ſaue him.</p>
            <p>If then there be any deſire in vs to obey the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; if any feare of erring to damnation; if any care of beleeuing aright to ſaluation, let vs labour to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the miſterie of iniquitie in the Romiſh faith: that knowing it, we may abhorre it, and may auoide: auoiding it we may embrace the loue of the truth, and be ſaued. What is it that leadeth thee out of the way to deſtruction? doth the glorious outward ſhew of the Popiſh Churches blinde or dazle thine eyes? It may perhaps admit ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in children, that they haue beene deceiued by ſuch toyes and gewgawes; But it is ridiculous and vntollerable for men to runne after ſights and ſhadowes. Surely if thou hadſt liued in our Sauiour Chriſts dayes, or his Apoſtles
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21008:52"/> times, thou wouldeſt haue choſen the Temple and the beauty thereof, with the Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſes, rather then the barren mountaines or wilderneſſe with our Lord and his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> But what is it that maketh thee a papiſt? diſcontent that thou art not honoured or inriched as thou deſireſt to be? Perhaps thou ouerualueſt thine owne worth, and thinkeſt there is more due to thee, then indeed there is; but ſay thou haſt not thy due? doeſt thou not know, that theſe things are ordered by the prouidence of God? ſhalt thou haue no cauſe of diſcontent if thou become a papiſt? are all papiſts r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpected and rewarded? I could name two great Earles, the experience of whoſe miſerie aboundantly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this conceite. Well, ſay thou attaine to all thou hopeſt for: the reckoning is behind; <hi>What ſhall it profit a man though he winne the whole world, if he looſe his owne ſoule? An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigone</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 8. 36.</note> in <hi>Sophocles</hi> was ſo wiſe, that when her ſiſter <hi>Iſmente</hi> demanded of her how ſhe durſt bury her brother <hi>Polinices</hi> body againſt <hi>Creons</hi> commandement, ſhe anſwered her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, like a noble Lady, that ſhe knew it was a duty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the gods, with whome ſhe was to liue longer, then vpon the earth with men: and therefore had more care to pleaſe them. Shall not this Lady, this heathen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne many men, many Chriſtians, that chooſe rather to enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, then to raigne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally in the glory of the Lord Ieſus in his heauenly Kingdome?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Doth antiquitie, vniuerſalitie, viſibilitie, conſent, like a loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtone draw thee after them? Antiquitie is then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a rule of truth, when the pedegree of it can be fetched from the beginning. For if euery opinion be truer, as it is ancienter, why ſhould not the Scribes and Phariſes traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, be of more account then our Sauiour Chriſts inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? certainely they had beene receiued and vſed in the Church of the Iewes many yeares before he was borne: yea they had vniuerſally the approbation and allowance of the whole Church: and continued in good liking, except
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21008:52"/> with a few that followed our Lord, for all his preaching, to the end of his life; what greater conſent could there be? all the Iewiſh Clergie, Prieſts, Leuites, Scribes, and Phariſes agreed as one man, to maintaine their owne ſuperſtitions, and keepe downe the religion of our Lord Ieſus; Theſe men the people depending vpon them, were, and had beene time out of minde the viſible Church. Oh that they had been as wiſe and learned as our papiſts now are, to haue called to our Sauiour for a Catalogue of their names, that had from time to time profeſſed the Religion which he ſought to bring in, contrary to that they held. doubtleſſe he muſt haue beene faine (vnleſſe he had vſed his diuine knowledge) to confeſſe, that at the leaſt, for the laſt 300 yeares, there was no ſuch beadroll of names to be found. I confeſſeſt Saint <hi>Luke</hi> in the geneallogy of our Sauiour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth the names of his anceſtours, who were queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe holy and religious worſhippers of God, and truſted in the Meſſiah to come. But I ſuppoſe it could hardly haue beene made plaine by any record of the Iewes (and yet they were more diligent and carefull in ſuch matters then Chriſtians haue beene) that the points wherein our Lord diſſented from the Scribes and Phariſes, were diſtinctly knowne, and publikely profeſſed by them one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> But of this matter, ſo much as concerneth the difference betwixt vs and the Church of Rome, I ſaid enough in the former Chapters, and will not repeate it needleſſely. This one remaineth for concluſion, that I humbly intreate all men which haue any true care of their own ſaluation, that they would not be carried away with words: but indeuour to enable themſelues to iudge how thoſe plauſible fancies, with which they are ſeduced, may be applied to proue that which is vndertaken thereby. To this end I haue employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelfe in this courſe: they that are deſirous to ſee the truth, may find direction therein for the iudging of it: and thereby arme themſelues againſt tho aſſaults, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of furious ſouldiers, and craftie pioners, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21008:53"/> their approches, and diſcouering their works, to the defeating of all their enterpriſes. The greateſt matter of all is, that you would embrace the loue of the truth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue with your ſelues, as thoſe glorious martyrs I ſpake of did, rather to indure torments and death, then to forſake the religion of the Lord Ieſus, or to ioyne in profeſſion with the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> This reſolution will bring ſafetie in peace, in war victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that no ill tidings ſhall affright you, no loſſes diſcourage you, no diſcontent turne you out of the right way. The Lord Ieſus himſelfe like the Angell in <hi>Ioſua,</hi> will march on the head of your troupes, and be as a cloud to refreſh you in the heate of Summer, and as a fire to warme you in the cold of winter: your ſwords ſhall eate the fleſh of your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, your pikes and bullets ſhall be drunke with their blood: one of you ſhall chaſe a thouſand, and an hundred of you put ten thouſand to flight: <hi>Babylon ſhall be caſt like</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math</note> 
               <hi>a milſtone into the ſea, and be found no more: you ſhall reward the ſcarlet-coloured ſtrumpet, as ſhe hath rewarded you, and giue her double according to her vvorkes, and in the cup that ſhe hath filled to you, fill her the double;</hi> to the glory of God that hath appointed her this puniſhment, the increaſe of religion, the ſafety of the State, and your honour in this life, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the life to come, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with the Father and the Holy Spirit, one God in three Perſons, be all glory, praiſe, obedience, and thankſgiuing now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21008:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
